<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvord of comfort. Or A discourse concerning the late lamentable accident of the fall of a roome, at a Catholike sermon, in the Black-friars at London, wherwith about fourscore persons were oppressed. Written for the comfort of Catholiks, and information of Protestants, by I.R. p</title>
            <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120899</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856092</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856092</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21611</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01012)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21611)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1202:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvord of comfort. Or A discourse concerning the late lamentable accident of the fall of a roome, at a Catholike sermon, in the Black-friars at London, wherwith about fourscore persons were oppressed. Written for the comfort of Catholiks, and information of Protestants, by I.R. p</title>
                  <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>58, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [at the English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno M.DC.XXIII. [1623]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.R. p. =  John Floyd, priest.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Tightly bound; some faded print and some pages stained.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Disasters --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21611:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21611:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A vvord of Comfort.</p>
            <p>OR A DISCOVRSE CONCERNING The late lamentable Accident of the fall of a roome, at a CATHOLIKE Sermon, in the <hi>Black-friars</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with about fourſcore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN <hi>For the Comfort of Catholiks, and Information of Proteſtants, By I. R. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed Anno M.DC.XXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21611:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21611:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET the duty of weeping for the Dead,<note place="margin">Tempus flendi Eccl. 3.6.</note> in this late diſmall Accident, ſo rufull to flesh and blood, which from our hartes both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Humanity and priuate Friendship en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force;<note place="margin">Tempus loquendi.</note> giue place vnto the duty of writing in the behalfe of the liuing, which at our han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des both Chriſtian Charity, and Prieſtly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation exact. Let Nature, which at this preſent makes me more willing to wett my paper with teares then with inke,<note place="margin">Ipſi pene viuendi vſui ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem hoc tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, nedu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtudijs. l. 2. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. Cap. 4. 31. Cap. 9. 1.</note> and (as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſayth of himſelfe in a like dolefull diſaſter) <hi>weary not only of ſtudying, but euen almoſt of liuing,</hi> that in lieu of penning diſcourſes of erudition and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I could much rather powre forth vntaught ſighs in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Ieremy</hi> his Threnes, <hi>Defecit anima mea propter Inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fectos: My ſoule is gone from me in ſorrow of them that are ſlayne:</hi> and, <hi>Quis dabit capiti meo aquam, &amp; ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis meis flumina lachrimarum, &amp; plorabo die ac nocte Interfectos filiae populi mei! Who will giue me water vnto my head and fluds of teares vnto mine eyes, that I may be wayle day and night the Slayne of my Country!</hi> Let (I ſay) this weake inclination of Nature yeeld vnto Gods holy will, and vnto the motion of heauenly Grace concurring with Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to preferre before priuate ſorrow for friendes, the publicke
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21611:3"/> defence of our Catholike Cauſe, ſeeing ignorant zeale is ready vpon any the least occaſion to diſgrace it. Let mourning for corporall Death, which the Holy Ghoſt confines within the compaſſe of ſeauen dayes,<note place="margin">Eccl. 22. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Luctus mortui ſeptem dies,</hi> eſpecially for them whoſe ſoules (as we with reaſon hope) do raigne in glory, be changed into mourning for <hi>blind Ignorance and Impiety,</hi> which the ſame Holy Spirit will haue commeaſured vnto the length of their life, <hi>luctus fatui &amp; impij omnes dies vitae eorum,</hi> to wit, ſo long as there is hope by teares of instruction to reclayme them.</p>
            <p>This Duty is neceſſary for foure ends, and vndertaken for the ſatisfaction of foure ſortes of perſons. First to refute their folly who with this darke mist of Gods <hi>vnſearchable Counſels,</hi> ſeeke to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the cleare light of his reuealed Doctrine, shyning in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church. Secondly, to still their teares who thinke they cannot weepe inough for their Friendes, not ſo much at their death, as at their being taken away by ſo strange and dreadfull a miſchance. Thirdly, to allay the wondering of them that ſecretly may complayne of the ſeuerity of Gods iudgments, that in theſe circumstances he would not ſpare his owne People, not ſpare his owne Name. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſomewhat aſſwage their ſorrow who grieue not for temporall reſpects,<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.3.</note> but <hi>their teares are to them bread day and night,</hi> to ſee Gods Enemyes inſult vpon his Church, &amp; to ſay vnto her, <hi>where is thy God?</hi> Which foure kinds of perſons styrred vp and troubled with different affections, by one, and the ſame commiſerable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shappe, we shall endeauour to quiet by foure kind of Arguments; by Teſtimonies of holy Scripture; by Examples of former Chriſtian tymes; by compariſon with ſome more prodigious euents vnto our Aduerſaries; finally by shewing Gods ends in the permiſsion of this Accident, of which we may make our Profit.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21611:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Comfort from the holy Scriptures.</head>
            <p>THere is not any greater affliction vnto Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants in this life, nor any more ſharpe corraſiue vnto their hart, then the happening of ſtrange &amp; dreadfull miſchances, that carry a ſhew of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger agaynſt their Religion, wherby the enemies therof harden their ſoules as ſtone, agaynſt it. And Gods Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Wiſdome, as he reſolued for reaſons beſt known to himſelfe, to deuide indifferently amongſt the good &amp; bad, theſe terrible caſualityes of mortall life: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in his Mercy,<note place="margin">Cui vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandae totum illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> librum vir Sapientiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putauit. Aug. l 10. de Ciuit. c. 3. The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher c. 8. 14.</note> he would haue his ſeruants warned heerof abundantly by his holy Word. For not only e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Booke of the diuine Scriptures be full of documents agaynſt this diſcomfort, but alſo (as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> noteth) one whole booke of that heauenly learning, to wit, that of <hi>Eccleſiastes,</hi> beginning, <hi>Vanity of Vanities, and all things va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> is entyrely ſpent in the proſecution of this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>That there is this Vanity vpon earth, that there be iust men vnto whome it happeneth according to the worke of the wicked: agayne there be wicked men vnto whome things happen as if they were iust,</hi> that ſo (ſayth the ſame Father) <hi>Men might loue the life that hath not Vanity vnder the ſunne, but verity vnder him that made the ſunne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of which booke I will alleadge only one ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, but the ſame ſo full, and ſo fit for our purpoſe,<note place="margin">Cap. 9. initio.</note> as it may ſeeme written a purpoſe by the ſpirit of Preſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to be vſed in this occaſion: <hi>This is the worſt of all things vnder the ſunne, that the ſame things happen alike vnto all, to the iuſt and to the wicked, to the good and to the bad, to the cleane and to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, to them that ſacrifice, and to them that contemne Sacrifice, to them that ſweare the Truth, and to them that are forſworne. Hence the hearts of the ſonnes of men are filled with malice &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in their life tyme, and afterward shallbe carried vnto Hell.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21611:4"/> To theſe wordes of the Holy Ghoſt, what can be added as more cleare in proofe of our Argument? what may be ſpoken more complete, proper, and pithy for our comfort in this accident?</p>
            <p>Heere by Gods holy Word we are informed that ſuch is his prouidence in this life, that an houſe or roome may fall, no leſſe vpon <hi>the Iuſt,</hi> as they are hearing his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Doctrine, then vpon <hi>the Wicked,</hi> as they are blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his bleſſed Name. No leſſe vpon <hi>the Good,</hi> that are weeping for pardon and remiſſion of their ſinnes; then vpon <hi>the Badde,</hi> that feaſt and banquet, riot and reioyce in their ſinnes. No leſſe vpon <hi>the Cleane,</hi> that by humble Confeſſion and penall Satisfaction purify their ſoules,<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.26.2.</note> then vpon the vncleane, <hi>whoſe wayes are at all tymes impure, the iudgments of God</hi> (by the doctrine of only Faith) <hi>being taken away from before their eyes.</hi> No leſſe vpon them that <hi>offer</hi> the Chriſtian vnbloody <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the immaculate Lambe, then vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that <hi>contemne</hi> this holy <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> &amp; would rather maſſacre the Prieſts that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate the ſame. Finally no leſſe vpon them that <hi>ſweare the Truth,</hi> that that doctrine is Chriſtian which from the mouth of Chriſt, by the vniuerſall cry of Chriſtian Preachers in all Ages hath byn ſucceſſiuely ſounded vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; then vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that depoſe their priuate conceyts gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their own inquiſition into Gods worde, to be the only Chriſtian diuine ſauing Truth, ſo filling the world with innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſſonant ſects. For as what fancy thinketh, that the bell ringeth: ſo what Hereſy imagineth, that in their conceyte the Scripture ſoundeth.</p>
            <p>This being ſo, why doth Hereſy inſult vpon Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in regard of an accident common vnto men, and vnto which their owne ſect is continually ſubiect? Why ſhould Charity be frighted to ſee ſuch deaths in their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Friends, that may happen, and often do happen vnto greateſt Saynts? Why doth Fayth complayne or wonder at this courſe of Gods prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which he hath ſet down to himſelfe in his Word, and which hath been ſtill his ordinany ſince the world? Why doth zeale grieue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21611:4"/> comfort to ſee the Church her enemies triumph, &amp; not rather pitty their caſe, that after a moment <hi>of malice and contempt, shall be carryed to burne for euer in Hell?</hi> The Holy Ghoſt doth acknowledge this kind of Croſſes to be the greateſt, <hi>the worst vnder the ſunne,</hi> yet not ſo ill vnto you the children of the Church, as vnto <hi>the ſonnes of men;</hi> I meane them, whoſe Religion as different from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike <hi>is humane,</hi> nothing but a denyall of high myſteries<note n="*" place="margin">As that the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſt is not bread, but the body of Chriſt. That the Saintes heare our prayers. That God aſſiſt his Church ſhe cannot erre. That the Body of Chriſt is in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places at once. That Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments worke Grace: Prieſts remit ſins &amp;c. Tobias c. 2.</note> contrary to the ſeeming of fleſh and bloud: Vnto theſe Humaniſts, I ſay, this accident is worſe, and cauſeth grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miſchiefe then vnto you. It doth grieue, and afflict your hart, it doth harden and obdurate their hart. It doth fill you with ſorrow and ſadnes, <hi>It filleth them with malice and contempt.</hi> It bringeth teares from your eyes, gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes from your breaſt, it fetcheth blaſphemyes from their mouths, iniuries from their handes. It makes you weary of mortall and miſerable life vnder the ſunne, not deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring comfort till you come to enioy with your Friends the felicity aboue the ſunne: It makes them ioy in the ſunne-ſhine of the greateſt vanity vnder the ſunne, not admitting of the light of Faith, that looketh aboue the ſunne; ſo continuing in their errours, vntill they be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from vnder the ſunne, vnto the greateſt myſery that is vnder the earth.</p>
            <p>Call to mind the Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the holy <hi>Tobias,</hi> in whom you may behold a patterne of your preſent afflicted ſtate. He was ſtrucken blind with ſwallows dunge falling into his eyes, when co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming home from burying the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of the faythfull that had been ſlayne, he caſt himſelf down vnder the wall of his houſe to ſleep, through wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines of pious labour, not able to go further. A ſtrange &amp; miſerable accident ſcarſe euer heard of before, ſent (as it might ſeeme) by the hand of Gods prouidence vpon him euen in his moſt feruent exerciſe of Religion.<note place="margin">Amici &amp; cognati eius deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debant e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. c. 2. v. 15.</note> Neyther was infidelity then wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting ſtraight to ſcorne and deride his piety, yea his owne countrymen and kindred inſulted vpon him. <hi>Where is thy hope for which thou didst good workes? Now thine almeſ-deedes appeare.</hi> As if they had ſayd: Now
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21611:5"/> the fruite of thy deedes of Charity is ſeene. Now thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of workes is brought to light. Thou art puniſhed with blindnes, that thou maiſt ſee thine own blindnes, to thinke that one by workes can pleaſe God, winne his loue, merit his fauour, purchaſe heauen. Thus did aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Infidelity ſpeake in the <hi>Puritan</hi> language, which now dayly ſoundes in our eares. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we know, that for God to ſend ſtrange diſaſters vpon his ſeruants hath been euer his cuſtome, wherby their Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath byn brought into ſcorne, and themſelues into ſorow, as now we are. In which occaſion on what can we better thinke for our comfort, then on the golden wordes of this glorious <hi>Toby,</hi> which he ſpake in anſwere vnto his deriders, ſhewing the Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his holy Aunceſtors that deliuered from hand to hand that doctrine vnto him, from which they had changed: <hi>Nolite ita loqui, quia FILII SANCTORVM ſumus, &amp; vitam illam expectamus, quam daturus est ijs qui Fidem ſuam NVNQVAM MVTANT ab eo.</hi> Do not ſpeake in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, becauſe we are the Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Saints, or holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and we exſpect that life which God will giue vnto them that NEVER CHANGE THEIR FAITH fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, vpon any accident, or occaſion whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Put before your eyes the patience of holy <hi>Iob,</hi> in that moſt rufull and horrible diſaſter, when all his ten Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with many ſeruants were oppreſſed by the fall of an houſe, togeather all once. Betwixt which accident and our miſchance there are ſo many ſimilitudes,<note place="margin">In domo fratris pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeniti Iob. 1 13. Le Filz aiſné de l'Egliſe. Hoc eſt Praecep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meum. Ioa. 15. 22. Orig. l. 1. in Iob.</note> corporall in their behalfe, ſpirituall on our ſide, as that may ſeeme to haue byn a figure of this. That happened in the houſe of the <hi>first begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne of Iob:</hi> This in his houſe who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the perſon of that King, that is tearmed <hi>the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt-begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sonne of the Church.</hi> They were oppreſſed as they were ſitting at the meate of their body: Theſe as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ghoſtly refection of their ſoule. They died as they were keeping a Feaſt in token of their fraternall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity and concord: Theſe as they were at a ſpirituall banquet, at a Sermon, wherin was preached vnto them <hi>the Christian Precepts of mutuall charity and loue.</hi> So the words
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21611:5"/> of <hi>Origen</hi> are true of them both, <hi>Tunc nouiſsimum vnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis &amp; concordia prandium pranderunt ſuper terram: In coelis nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aeternae gloriae &amp; incorruptionis beatitudine pariter fruuntur.</hi> The cauſe of that ſlaughter was Satan in malice agaynſt the Religion of their Father; The cauſe of this ſlaughter was the ſame Satan (for he is the Author of all euill) in hatred of the Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their Fore-fathers, &amp; of the Holy Catholike Church their Mother.<note place="margin">See Titel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus in Iob. Factu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio Heb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domadae. ita para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſis Chaldai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca. Iob. 1.5.</note> They were ſlayne <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the circle of the ſeauen dayes were runne about,</hi> on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both when in the morning before, they had byn ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>by the ſacrifice of their holy Father, offering an Holocauſt for euery one;</hi> Theſe alſo were ſlayne when the weeke was expired, on the day of the Chriſtian Sabboth, when (the moſt of them at leaſt) had byn ſanctified in the morning by the Chriſtian moſt pure Sacrifice, and by being parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Sacrament, or Holocauſt of Chriſt his moſt pretious Body and Bloud, giuen whole and entire ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to euery one.</p>
            <p>Compare your caſe with that of this holy Prophet, and conſider what reaſon of comfort he had, which you haue not much more ſtrong? what cauſe of ſorow you haue, which he had not in greater meaſure? what ſolace had <hi>Iob</hi> that you want? That his Children ſo ſuddainly ſlayne were of holy life?<note place="margin">Lib. 1. in Iob.</note> The ſame you may preſume of theſe your Friendes: and take the wordes of <hi>Origen</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing equally vnto them both. <hi>They were ſimple and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere of hart, chast and pure in ſoule, of vnſpotted conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of God, deare to his Angels for their innocency, full of brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charity one towards another, not any did, or could ſpeake of them an euill word.</hi> That they had byn ſanctified not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the ſacrifices then in vſe? Theſe alſo on the very ſame day were expiated by the Chriſtian Sacraments, &amp; by a ſacrifice of a farre greater force, yea of infinite price.<note place="margin">De ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loquentes &amp; cum ſororibus &amp;c.</note> That they died holily in an action of brotherly charity and loue? In a farre more holy action and exerciſe of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were theſe taken away: that what <hi>Origen</hi> ſayth of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is much more certayne of theſe. <hi>They were taken as they were diſcourſing of Piety and Sanctity among themſelues, honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21611:6"/> God in their hartes, prayſing him as their Creatour, adoring him as their Benefactour, giuing him thankes as vnto their Foster-father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Filij ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſſimi Patris.</note> 
               <hi>As little Innocents ſit and ſtand, play and ſport togeather without any malice or vncleanes in minde, ſo were theſe holy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of their most holy Father, when the blow came vpon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide, what cauſe haue you of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that did not preſſe more heauily vpon the fatherly hart of holy <hi>Iob?</hi> You haue loſt them that were deare vnto you; but not more deare then was vnto him his whole family of children. A ſtroake (ſayth <hi>Origen</hi>) whereof none can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend the dolefulnes, but ſuch as know by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce what is the loue of a Father, though the ſole imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof may moue any mans hart vnto teares of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>He loſt his Sonnes whom he had nourished, to whom he had giuen best education,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. l. 1. in Iob.</note> 
               <hi>that now were come to ripe yeares; His Sons whom he had brought vp in piety, ſeaſoned with the feare and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe of God, ſettled in charity and mutuall loue, made in all kind of ſanctity like to himſelf; His Sonnes whoſe yſſue he did deſire to ſee, whoſe poſterity he did ſo earneſtly expect, from whom in his old age he did hope for comfort; Theſe Sonnes, and not they only, but alſo his Daughters, ſo chaſt, ſo pure, ſo religious, immaculate, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blemish, on whoſe heades on the day of their mariage he did intend to ſet garlands of ioy.</hi> All theſe periſhed togeather at once, and togeather with them, <hi>ſpes quanta nepotum!</hi> all his ioyfull hopes of glorious ofspring.</p>
            <p>The death of your Friendes was dreadfull, horrible, wherof the very remembrance is execrable, how much more the ſight? Not more rufull &amp; terrible then the death of the holy Children of this bleſſed Patriarke, which <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> deſcribes in theſe wordes?<note place="margin">Orig. vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>They dyed not an ordinary but a moſt lamentable death, they were moſt miſerably ſlayne. Their bodyes were torne in peeces with ſtones, bruyſed with the weight of beames, couered and defiled with duſt, lime and rubbish. Mamocks of their torne flesh, togeather with peeces of their broken bones, their braynes, their bowells, their bloud, the brothers with their ſiſters, the ſiſters with their brothers lay mingled with clay, morter and ſtone in one inſeparable maſſe. For the Diuell left nothing of them entyre, not their ſculls, not their bowels, not their ſtomackes, not their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21611:6"/> armes, not their handes, not their leggs, not their feete, in ſumme not any part of their body. A rufull ſpectacle, a wofull ſight, yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no ſpectacle, no fight at all. For nothing was to be ſeen, nothing that could be known, flesh and bones, ſtones and timber, clay and morter, bloud and wine lay ſo confuſedly togeather in one heape; Neyther the maiſters from the ſeruants, nor the brothers from the ſiſters, nor his children among themſelues were diſcernable the one from the other, eyther by their faces, or by their perſons.</hi> Thus dyed the holy &amp; innocent Children of <hi>Iob,</hi> whoſe death yet was deare and precious in Gods ſight, that we might not iudge of the ſanctity of mens liues, by the hydeous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hew of their deaths.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Iob</hi> his Religion (you will ſay) was not reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in regard of this accident. Yes, and perchance much more then the Catholike now is, in reſpect of this late <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent.</hi> For I am perſwaded that all moderate Proteſtants behold this miſchance with the eye of pitty, as a miſery indifferently incident vnto mankind, not with eyes of diſdayne, as an argument of iuſt contempt of the Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them that ſtood obnoxious therunto. Neyther do I thinke, that they, vnto whome indiſcreet auerſion from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing of our Church hath giuen the name of <hi>Pure,</hi> do preſſe this fall as a iuſt reaſon, to fall from our Religion, except they be ſo voyd of diſcretion and vnwiſe, as to make the truth of GODS Word, which will not fayle though heauen &amp; earth paſſe away, to depend on the ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or falling of an houſe. If ſome, whom the tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities they haue gotten, by the baniſhment of our Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> engage, and late, vayne, and idle feares of looſing what they haue gotten, enrage againſt the Roman Church; if theſe men (I ſay) by their declamations in pulpit, incenſe the rude vulgar multitude to take this occaſion to inſult vpon our Religion,<note place="margin">Beato Iob inſultaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Reges. Tob. 2.15.</note> they do no more vnto vs then was alſo done vnto the moſt holy <hi>Iob</hi> in his diſtreſſe by the <hi>Miniſters of Satan.</hi> For who knowes not, how he was <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted and iuſulted vpon,</hi> by them that vpon the newes of his miſhapp, came to comfort him;<note place="margin">Orig. l. 1. in Iob.</note> 
               <hi>but the Diuell changed their hartes into bitternes agaynst him, filled their mouths with bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemyes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21611:7"/> and iniurious wordes.</hi> So that in place of conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they fell to reproach his Religion, vrging the ſayd miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance to condemne his ſincerity of diuine ſeruice, &amp; true practiſe of piety.</p>
            <p>Wherfore as you are the conſorts of holy <hi>Iob</hi> in your triall, ſo be like vnto him in your truſt and confidence in God, and from his goodnes expect, in deuout ſilence, the like reward of your conſtancy, not only a crowne of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in the next world, but alſo increaſe of temporall comfort in the preſent.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Comfort by the Examples of former Chriſtian tymes.</head>
            <p>THe comfort of holy Scripture, is ſeconded by the practiſe of Gods Prouidence in the Chriſtian Church,<note place="margin">Quaecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſunt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moda, Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis ſunt cum cete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſine exceptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munia. Cyp. ſer. de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</note> which hath been ſtill ſubiect vnto the dreadfull miſchances of mortality, no leſſe then other men, wherby both <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Heretikes</hi> haue byn moued to inſult vpon the Catholike Chriſtians, as I ſhall demonſtrate by diuers Examples of the firſt ſix hundred yeares, during which tyme moſt Proteſtants dare not ſay that Chriſtianity was vnſound.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Examples within the firſt three hundred yeares.</head>
               <p>BEing to alleadge Examples of dreadfull deaths, and miſchances happened vnto Saints ſince the Chriſtian tymes, where can I better beginne then with Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus himſelfe,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2. Eph. 1.22. Rom. 8.19.</note> 
                  <hi>the founder of our Fayth, the accomplisher of our Hope, the head of the Chriſtian elect, the Patterne of perfection, according to the modell wherof the Saints of God are framed.</hi> Could the eternall Father deſigne for his beloued Sonne
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21611:7"/> any kind of death more diſmall and pittifull, more diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cefull and horrible then that of the Croſſe? A death infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous vnto the Gentile, execrable vnto the Iew,<note place="margin">Maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctushomo qui pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>det in ligno. Deut. 21.23.</note> branded with a curſe by Gods owne word. Which Croſſe though he imbraced out of his voluntary choyce and infinite cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind, yet that the ſame might ſeeme more ignominious in the eye of the world, he would haue things carryed in ſuch ſort, as if againſt his will his enemyes, through the treachery of his diſciple, &amp; ſtrength of their practiſes had preuayled to lay that horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble death vpon him. This courſe of prouidence, God vſed towards Chriſt Ieſus the Saint of Saints, for the Comfort of Chriſtian Saints, amongſt whome (as Saint <hi>Angustin</hi> writes) <hi>Multi multarum mortium faeda varietate conſumpti ſunt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 1. de ciuit. c. 11.</note> Many haue byn deſtroyed with ſtrange variety of dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deaths. By this Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple we are taught, that (as ſayth the ſame excellent Doctour) <hi>No death is euill which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell of good life: That death is made miſerable, not by the miſeryes that go before it, but by the miſeryes that follow vpon it: That men (ſeeing they muſt of neceſsity dye) are to regard not the horrour of the miſchance by which they are taken away, but the quality of the place they are by death carryed vnto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as Chriſt Ieſus in regard of the dignity of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is without peere, ſo this example by reaſon of the ſtrangenes therof, ſhall paſſe as incomparable, and not to be put in number with the reſt. I will therfore poſe proud preſumers that dare determine when, &amp; on whome God ſendeth his vengeance, with the different kind of proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he ſhewed towards two Roman Emperours of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary diſpoſitions, to wit, <hi>Caius Caligula,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Senec co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolat. ad Heb. Quid ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma vitia in ſumma fortuna poſſint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hieron. de obitu Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potiani.</note> and <hi>Titus Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſianus:</hi> The one ſurnamed the monſter of mankind, <hi>whom Nature</hi> (as Seneca writes) <hi>may ſeeme to haue brought forth to no other end, then that in him as in a glaſse, it might appeare vnto what extremity of wickednes man may arriue, when the baſeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition vnto vice, and the higheſt condition of Prince, meete togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame perſon:</hi> The other ſurnamed <hi>Delitiae generis humani,</hi> The ioy and pleaſure of mankind, in whom was ſeene a ſecret neuer before, nor perchance ſince ſeen in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21611:8"/> world,<note place="margin">Nec caedes fecit nec amoribus inſeruiuit comis &amp; continens adeo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſtatim mutauit. Sueton. in Tito. c. 11. Dio, &amp; Sueton in Caio. Dio &amp; Sueton in Tito. Philo de legat. ad Caium.</note> one made better that is mild, modeſt, chaſt, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and courteous, by being rayſed vnto the height and dignity of Emperour. I will not ſtande to rehearſe the barbarous crueltyes of <hi>Caligula,</hi> without any cauſe vſed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his neareſt kindred and friendes; nor the incredible clemencyes of <hi>Titus</hi> towards his enemyes, and euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that he knew by dayly practiſes went about to ſhorten his life. This I may further affirme, that the firſt, to wit <hi>Caius,</hi> was an enemy of true Religion, or rather a bloudy perſecutour of all Religion, cauſing himſelf eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where to be adored as the only God, with murders and maſſacres of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that would not yeeld vnto this impiety. <hi>Titus</hi> on the other ſide a friend and fauourer of Chriſtians, who ſtayed the perſecution that <hi>Nero</hi> had rayſed againſt them. Oh into what danger of erring do they precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, that preſume they can diue into the depth of Gods ſecrets, and will iudge of men, and Religion by diſaſterous euents! For the dayes of the Empire of the moſt wicked <hi>Caius</hi> were full of proſperity,<note place="margin">Sueton. in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io. c. 31.</note> no misfortune of warre, no famines, no plagues, no burning of townes, no earth-quakes, no falling of houſes, in ſo much as the barbarous Tyrant was grieued thereat, wiſhing that his Empire by ſome memorable calamity, might be made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned vnto poſterity. On the other ſide, what of the ſhort Empire of <hi>Titus?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sueton. in Tito. c 8.</note> The ſame was from the beginning to the end infeſted with dreadfull aduerſityes, with fires from heauen, with earth-quakes ſo ſtrange and hydeous, as the like were neuer heard off before, nor recorded in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hiſtory:<note place="margin">Dion in Tito. Incendiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, diuinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potius quam hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum id malum fuit.</note> wherwith not only townes and cittyes, but many whole countryes were layd waſt and deſtroyed, chiefly the citty of Rome, with all the moſt excellent or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments therof. Theſe calamityes were the cauſe that he pined away with ſorrow to the great griefe of all good men, particularly of Chriſtians; his death being alſo haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with poyſon giuen him by <hi>Domitian</hi> his vnnaturall Brother, whoſe cruelty he could neuer ouercome with all kind of curteſies, clemencies, and tokens of more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brotherly loue. Who conſidering theſe things, will not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21611:8"/> reſt aſtoniſhed at Gods inueſtigable iudgments? Who will not with the Prophet acknowledge,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>that he is terrible in his counſels aboue the Sonnes of men?</hi> Specially ſeeing Infidels tooke this occaſion of calamityes happening vpon this Emperour the friend of Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Tertul. Apolog. cap. 40.</note> otherwiſe ſo iuſt and benigne, to calumniate their Religion, as if all miſeryes were ſent vpon the world in regard of them? which ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous conceyt by this accident of <hi>Titus</hi> his vnfortunate raigne, tooke ſuch roote in the hart of Pagans,<note place="margin">Aug. l. 1. de Ciuit. c. 2.</note> as it neuer afterward went out, ſo long as they breathed within the Roman Empire.</p>
               <p>Heerin they were confirmed by the ſucceſſe of the raigne of <hi>Gordian</hi> the Emperour, a friend of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if not alſo a worſhipper of Chriſt ſecretly,<note place="margin">See the life of S. Cecily Virg. and Mart. Iulius Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitolin. in Gordia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. Niſſen. in vita Greg. Thaum. Ciuitates omnes &amp; quae circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> circa Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giones. Cyp. ſerm de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. Orig. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Col. l. 3.</note> and in hart. In the beginning of his Empire, when he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden the perſecution rayſed againſt Chriſtians, by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximinus</hi> the <hi>Thracian</hi> his bloudy &amp; barbarous Predeceſſor, preſently happened <hi>most horrible Earth-quakes, wherwith whole Cittyes with all the people dwelling therin perished, and were ſwallowed vp aliue by the opening of the ground;</hi> many of them without queſtion being Chriſtians of very holy life. For Chriſtians were then ſo multiplied, <hi>as they filled all Cittyes, Townes, and almost Villages of the Roman Empire:</hi> and S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian beareth witneſſe that in all kind of calamityes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, Peſtilence, ſacke of Cittyes, ſhipwrackes, Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes &amp;c. Chriſtians were deſtroyed &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, as much as any other.</p>
               <p>By which Miſchances the hartes of Infidels were har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened againſt Religion, euen as much as new Sectaries are in this Age, wherof <hi>Origen</hi> liuing at that tyme doth complayne in theſe wordes. <hi>Denuo calumniatores noſtritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum motuum cauſamin multitudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fidelium conferre coeperu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quod non impugnemur à Principibus ſicut ſuperiori tempore:</hi> Heere agayne our calumnious Aduerſaries, layd the cauſe of ſo miſerable miſchances vpon the multitude of the Faythfull dayly increaſing, becauſe now we are not perſecuted by our Princes as in former tymes. Behold the auncient lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Infidelity, which hereſie eſpecially by hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21611:9"/> Purity now hath made the vulgar Engliſh of our Country, wherby it may appeare, that both <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> impugne the ſame Church, and that both are moued to <hi>ſpeake by the ſame ſpirit,</hi> ſeeing they vtter their mind ſo iuſt in the ſame forme of wordes.</p>
               <p>Neyther was this the firſt inſultation of Infidels ouer Chriſtians in that Age, in regard of miſchances, nor was this the firſt occaſion they tooke of hardening their harts as ſtone agaynſt them. A little before happened the lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table murder of <hi>Alexander Seuerus a most iust Emperour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lampri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandro.</note> 
                  <hi>a great admirer of Chriſtian Religion,</hi> yea <hi>Mammea</hi> his Mother was eſteemed a Chriſtian. <hi>He kept in his Cabinet a picture of Chriſt, he exhorted Pagans to imitate the ſanctity of Chriſtians; when men were punished for any crime of in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ustice, he did vſe by the voyce of the cryer to proclayme that Christian ſentence,</hi> Quod tibi non vis, alteri ne feceris. Finally he was reſolued to haue built a <hi>Temple vnto Christ,</hi> where Chriſtians might worſhip him: but the <hi>Pagan</hi> South-ſayers oppoſed againſt it, affirming (euen as hereſy now doth (for all errour is guilty to its owne weaknes) OMNES <hi>Christianos futuros, &amp; reliqua templa deſerenda,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lampri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandro.</note> that then all would become Chriſtians, &amp; no other Temple be frequented. When I ſay this iuſt and good Emperour, ſuch a louer of Chriſtians was ſlayne, a moſt horrible earth-quake following therupon in moſt partes of the world, by which Chriſtians were particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly conſumed, it is incredible what an out-cry and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore was rayſed by the ſeditious worſhippers of falſe Gods agaynſt them, wherof <hi>Origen</hi> then alſo liuing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention, &amp; complayneth ſaying: <hi>Earth-quakes happen euen alſo amongst vs in ſundry places,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Origen. in Ioan. tom. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>with the ruines of houſes &amp; ſwallowing vp of many people; the impious deuoyd of fayth, crying euery where that to punish Chriſtians ſuch earth-quakes are. And not only theſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Firmil. in Epiſt. ad Cyprian. quae eſt 75 inter Ep. Cyprian.</note> 
                  <hi>but they that ſeemed wiſe did in publicke affirme, that theſe Earth-quakes in regard of Christians were cauſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firmilianus</hi> a Biſhop liuing in that Age affirmes, that ſuch miſeryes and ſtrange vengeances, ſome of them were <hi>priuatae Chriſtianis, fell vpon Chriſtians only:</hi> as alſo <hi>Origen</hi> inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuats in the former wordes, <hi>euen amongſt vs earth-quakes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen.</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21611:9"/> And <hi>Firmilianus</hi> addeth, that theſe earth-quakes were rayſed by the inchantment and witchery of a woman profeſſing her ſelfe a Chriſtian, and a Propheteſſe, being (as it is likely) of <hi>Montanus</hi> his ſect, which then was in ſtrength. Who will not wonder at Gods holy permiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſuch miſeryes ſhould be inflicted vpon Chriſtians, (as aunciently vpon holy <hi>Iob</hi>) by an hereticall Witch, ſo making Religion a ſcorne &amp; obloquy amongſt Infidels: As alſo this our miſchance, though there was a naturall apparent cauſe therof, yet we need not doubt but Sathan therin had ſecretly his hand. But in theſe permiſſions and dolefull accidents we cannot ſay vnto God, Why doeſt thou ſo? We muſt with holy <hi>Iob</hi> and the auncient chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, lay our ſelues proſtrate at his feete, in the ſilence and ſorrow of ſoule,<note place="margin">Iudici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dei abyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus multa. Pſal. 35. &amp; Pſal. 118.72.</note> drowning our ſhallow ſelfe-humane wiſdome <hi>in the bottomles depth of his iudgments,</hi> crying as they did with the Prophet, <hi>Thou art iust (O Lord) and righteous are thy iudgments.</hi> And agayne: <hi>The iudgments of God are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed within themſelues,</hi> though out of themſelues, and vnto vs their iuſtification doth not alwayes appeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſcandall of Infidels and Heretiks, at the lamentable deſtruction of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> and <hi>Nicea.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFTER <hi>Constance</hi> had ſet vp the profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion euery where in the world, in the dayes of his Sonne <hi>Constantius,</hi> the whole Citty of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> the place which ſo many chriſtian Martyrs had conſecrated with the precious effuſion of their bloud, with Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes and fire was vtterly deſtroyed, being then not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſtian, but alſo Catholike, or the moſt part,<note place="margin">Ammian. Marcellin. l. 17.</note> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by S. <hi>Vrſacius</hi> his communion with them in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Prayers.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>This miſerable miſchance is by <hi>Ammi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> deſcribed in theſe wordes. <hi>Straight after the breake of day, a ſuddayne concourſe and thickning togeather of darke cloudes tooke away the ſight of the ſunne, which was ryſen cleere vnto the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21611:10"/> world, ſo that for want of light men could not ſee things that were neere vnto them, and which they touch't with their handes.</hi> Then as if God had reſolued to ſend a fatall deſtruction vpon them, calling the windes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foure coaſts of the world for that purpoſe, behold a moſt horrible fury of ſtormes inuaded the Citty. An hydeous noyſe was heard from the mountayns round about ſhaken with the violence of the winds, as alſo from the ſhore beaten with the rage of roaring waues. Heerupon enſued horrible whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>windes with ſuch dreadfull ſhaking of the ground, as therewith both the Citty and the Suburbs were ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne. And as a great part of the citty ſtood vpon the ſide of hills, buildings fell one vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, men langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing away with feare and griefe through the moſt rufull noyſe cauſed, aſwell by the cracking of houſes that fell on euery ſide, as alſo with the lamentable cryes &amp; ſchriches of men and women, bewayling the loſſe of parents, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbands, wiues and children, and whatſoeuer elſe by the band of kindred was neere and deare vnto them.</p>
                  <p>At two of the clocke after dinner ſomewhat before three, the ſunne ſhined out of the cloudes cleere and bright, as it were ſmiling at their miſery, and comming a purpoſe to diſcouer vnto them, and lay before their eyes as it were vpon a Theater, the whole moſt execrable ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of that rufull ſlaughter. Many vnder the ruines pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; chruſht in peeces by the weight of things that fell vpon them. Some couered in the rubbiſh vp to very necke, only their heades being out, might haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued if any had giuen them their helping hand, who for want of ſuccor periſhed. Others hunge in the ayre vpon the end of beames and rafters, which had pierced into their bowels, and through their bodyes. Many hundreds lay togeather in one heape ſlayne at one clapp; a little before, a company of liuing men, now nothing els but a mangled multitude of deformed corſes. Diuers within their owne houſes were with ruines round about inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and impriſoned aliue and ſound, to be conſumed with anguiſh and hunger, amongſt whome <hi>Aristenaetus</hi> gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21611:10"/> of the towne, breathed out his ſoule by the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a long death. Some in their falling had their heades bruyzed &amp; broken one agaynſt another, ſome their leggs, ſome their thighs, ſome their armes, ſome their very ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſtroke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their bodies, who lay groning betwixt life and death, with moſt pittifull cryes and obſecrations, imploring the ayde of them that were in the ſame miſery. A great part of that infortunate Citty, alwell of Churches as of houſes and men, might notwithſtanding this cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity haue remayned, had not terrible globes of flame iſſued out of houſes, which wandering euery where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Citty for fifty dayes and fifty nights, conſumed into aſhes whatſoeuer was obnoxious vnto fire. Thus <hi>Ammianus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>This dreadfull deſtruction of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> was cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a vengeance of God agaynſt Chriſtian and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe it happened at the ſame tyme whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt the errour of <hi>Photinus,</hi> and <hi>Aetius,</hi> a Councell of Biſhops was thyther ſummoned to be held.<note place="margin">Sozom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 4. c. 15.</note> The Biſhops were in their way, yea ſome (though few) already ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued who periſhed with the reſt. Amongſt others, that moſt holy man <hi>Vrſacius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſcopus Nicome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae &amp; alij ex Boſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoro. Sozom. ibid.</note> that had byn a glorious Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of Chriſt, in the perſecution of <hi>Licinius,</hi> who forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the court of the Emperour, hauing giuen away all to the poore, there lead an heauenly forme of Monaſticall life in continuall faſting and prayer, renowned alſo for miracles, as caſting out of Diuels, and by a word only killing a Dragon that infeſted the citty, who likewyſe had foretold this calamity, wiſhing the cittizens, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly the Prieſts, by pennance and prayer to ſeeke to preuent the ſame. This great Saint I ſay, put into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Martyrologe, was found dead in his cell,<note place="margin">Martyrol. Roman. 16. Aug.</note> or little cottage he had built to himſelf, lying proſtrate on his face as he did vſe in his prayers, eyther ſtifled with the ſmoake of the fire, or els dying in his prayer out of griefe: For he had deſired of God that he might not liue after the deſtruction of that citty, wherin he had byn made a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, &amp; afterward profeſſed the ſtate of Euangelicall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21611:11"/> The death of this holy man &amp; of many others, was taken of Infidels as diuine vengeance vpon Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Religion, ſo that full of ioy they went triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phing vnto the Emperour, and mingling falſhood with truth ſayd, That the whole multitude of Chriſtian Biſhops and Prieſts, men, women, and children, had byn ſlayne by the ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of their Gods, within their very Churches, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were fled for ſecurity and ſuccour:<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gno E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui ſacrae doctrinae fauebant dolore.</note> yea that the famous Temple built vnto Chriſt, by <hi>Constantine</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was vtterly from the very foundation razed, as indeed it was to the great grief of the orthodoxe Biſhops, eſpecially in regard of the ſcandall that Heretikes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels tooke therat. Wherby the vanity and head-long blindnes of our Aduerſaries may appeare, who inſult vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Catholiks in regard of a vulgar euent, a very trifle in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of this. But ſomething they muſt haue that may giue them occaſion to rayle at our Religion, which by reaſon they cannot impugne, no nor dare looke vpon it truly related, they know the ſame to be ſo warrantable.</p>
               <p>Not altogeather ſo terrible, yet in reſpect of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the tyme more ſcandalous was the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſtruction of the citty of <hi>Nicea,</hi> where the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian generall Councell was celebrated agaynſt the <hi>Aria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> and the doctrine of <hi>Homouſion,</hi> or Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiality defined. When <hi>Valence</hi> the Arian Emperour began to perſecute the <hi>Nicen</hi> Fayth, ſome few yeares after his being come to the Empire, iuſt at the ſame tyme the Citty of <hi>Nicea</hi> was ouerthrown from the very fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dations by an earth-quake. Saint <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> tearmeth this earth-quake the greateſt that had happened within the memory of man. whereby his holy Brother <hi>Caeſarius</hi> then the Emperours Receauer, was in danger, and miraculouſly eſcaped. For being couered within the rubbiſh of the ruines, the ſame were a defence vnto him agaynſt further miſchiefe, till he was thence taken out a little hurt, and thereupon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to giue ouer the world. Heere the <hi>Arians</hi> did tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph agaynſt the Catholiks of that tyme, (euen as ſome hoat Puritans doe now agaynſt vs) as if God togeather
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21611:11"/> with the Emperour, heauen togeather with earth had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired agaynſt the <hi>Nicene</hi> doctrine, of Chriſts being Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and Conſubſtantiall vnto God his Father. Theſe our Antagoniſts that are ſo iolly and iocund, ſo puffed vp with pride at the fall of a rotten chamber vpon ſome few at a Catholike ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where no doctrine was then prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched which they dare ſay was contrary vnto theirs; how inſolent and intollerable would they be, if the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſhould turne to be of their Sect, and perſecute the Catholike Fayth; and that iuſt in that coniunction, the Citty of <hi>Trent,</hi> with the Church and place where the Councell did meete, and made their Decrees, ſhould by ſome earth-quake or lightening from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be deſtroyed. And yet ſhould they haue no greater argument agaynſt the <hi>Tridentine,</hi> then the <hi>Arians</hi> had agaynſt the <hi>Nicene</hi> defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of Fayth. Whence one may gather how vayne, empty and deſtitute of ſolide cauſes of ioy their hart, and their Religion is, that do ſo much triumph at a trifle, wherby they make not their ſtrength of Fayth, but their weaknes of iudgment, and want of charity, manifeſt vnto the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="strange and wonderful" type="examples">
               <head>Other Examples strange and wonderfull.</head>
               <p>HOw much did Infidels reioyce when the Chriſtians of <hi>Moguntia</hi> were ſlayne by the <hi>Barbarians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ammian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> l. 20.</note> not as Chriſtians in hatred of their Religion, for then they had byn happy martyrs, but as ſubiects of the Roman Empire, and out of their auerſion from the ſame, which <hi>S. Hierome</hi> deplores, ſaying:<note place="margin">Hier. ep. 11. ad Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gut.</note> 
                  <hi>Moguntiacum</hi> in former tymes a famous and glorious Citty, is now deſtroyed, and many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands murdered within the very Church. As alſo in the death of <hi>Iouian</hi> Emperour, that vnder <hi>Iulian</hi> had ſuffered perſecution, and preſently vpon the death of <hi>Iulian,</hi> was by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the army choſen Emperour.<note place="margin">Ammian. l. 25.</note> When Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were fulleſt of ioy, glorying that the Empire was giuen him of God, in reward of his conſtancy in Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21611:12"/> Religion,<note place="margin">Iouianus guſtatis tantùm Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum foetore, ſuffocatus eſt. Hier. ep. ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liodo. de morte Nepot. Socrates l. 7. c. 38.</note> in the mid'ſt of their acclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; triumphs, he was taken away by ſuddane death, choaked with the ſmoake of coles, in the 7. moneth of his Empire.</p>
               <p>How did the <hi>Nouatians</hi> exult agaynſt the Catholiks, when in a moſt ſtrange and horrible conflagration of the Citty of Conſtantinople, all the chiefe monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the citty &amp; Catholike Churches being waſted with fire, only the <hi>Nouatian</hi> Church or meeting place for prayer eſcaped, the houſes rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about being al in a flame. Which they did attribute vnto the prayers of their Biſhop, who was then praying in their Church, and in memory of that ſuppoſed miracle did early keep a ſolemne feaſt; and yet after their triumps &amp; inſultatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s agaynſt Catholike, their ſect vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away, &amp; within ſhort time after, there was ſcarſe any memory therof, which wilbe alſo the end of theſe torre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of errour that novv ſwell with waters, and keep a noyſe in the world. How great was the ioy of the <hi>Pagans,</hi> when at the time of the baniſhment of <hi>S. Chryſostome,</hi> the Church of Conſtantinople being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed with caſuall, or with procured, or (as other rather thinke) miraculous fire, togeather with the Emperours pallace, &amp; houſe of the Senate? all Chriſtian monuments were waſted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, and in particular the Statua's of <hi>Constantine,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the great, the two Chriſtian Emperours whom Idolatry did moſt deteſt, yet two images or Idols, the one of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and the other of <hi>Minerua,</hi> were found in the confuſed maſſe of aſhes vntoucht: Infidels did interprete this prodigy that the Gods had not forſaken the Empire, but would agayne returne. Which fooliſh conceyte of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, was but a lightening before death, ſeing preſently the Gothes preuayling, togeather with their entrance, Paganiſme was wholly &amp; vtterly extinct, not any pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe therof being left in the Empire.</p>
               <p>I will conclude with one more Example of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouidence, in afflicting his ſeruants the Orthodoxe Chriſtians, in ſuch ſort that in the iudgment of men and Hereſy he might ſeeme to miſlike their Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Antioch,</hi> being by ſituation of the place ſubiect to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21611:12"/> earth-quakes was free and quiet from ſuch miſchances, in the gouernment of three Eutychian Emperours <hi>Zeno, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliſcus,</hi> and <hi>Anastaſius,</hi> for the ſpace of threeſcore and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeares, Hereſy reioycing and floriſhing therein.<note place="margin">Euagrius l. 4. c. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> the moſt Catholike Prince ſucceeding them in the Empire, the Catholiks of Antioch were exceedingly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted to ſee their long perſecution now at end. For, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerus</hi> the <hi>Eutichian,</hi> and head of the <hi>Acephali</hi> being expeld, a Catholike Patriarke was ordayned in his place, choſen by the Pope and the Emperour,<note place="margin">Ammian. l. 3. c. 6.</note> with exact care to giue the afflicted Antiochians the beſt they could find. The Catholiks being full of content in reſpect of this change, and peace, after ſo long moleſtations, God in his ſecret iudgments would alay their wine with water, their ioyes with ſorow. For their Biſhop being come, behold a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan earth-quake ſurpriſeth the citty, at dinner tyme, as they were at meate. And a whirle-wind ryſing vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natly at that very inſtant, blew the fire and flame of the kitchins, then burning according to the tyme of the day, vpon the buildings that were ſhaken by the earth-quake. So the commiſerable citty ſet vpon by a double miſchiefe and enemy togeather at once, was deſtroyed with the moſt of her inhabitants: amongſt them was her Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and holy Biſhop <hi>Euphraſius,</hi> who (his head being firſt ſtroken off by the fall of a pillar) was buried in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of fire, to the exceſſiue ioy of the <hi>Eutychians,</hi> and <hi>Seuerus</hi> their ring-leader, but to the great lamentation of Catholiks, ſpecially of the good Emperour.<note place="margin">Paulus Diaconus in Miſcell. l. 15.</note> For vpon newes heerof he put off his Diademe and purple, veſted himſelfe in ſacke-cloth, ſate ſolitary many weekes togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weeping in ſilence, not admitting of any mirth, though the dayes were ſolemne and feſtiuall, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which his cuſtome was to goe with great pompe and ſplendour vnto the Church. Where alſo we may note, that the ioy the <hi>Eutychians</hi> tooke in this miſchance, was but the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of death, ſeeing preſently heereupon they were ſo rooted out, that in the hyſtories of the next ſucceeding Age, there is no memory of them.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21611:13"/>
               <p>As Catholiks haue cauſe of comfort in theſe Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to ſee things ſucceed with them, as they did with the orthodoxe Chriſtians and Saints of God in former ages, ſo likewiſe our Cenſurers, that making themſelues of <hi>Gods Priuy Counſell</hi> giue out their Writs agaynſt vs, may tremble, to ſee themſelues hardened in malice, as former Heretiks were, and to feele the ſame lightenings of death as they did. And for concluſion of this Chapter, I will agayne repeate the wordes of the Holy Ghoſt wherwith I beganne, in which Catholiks may receaue comfort, &amp; our inſulting Aduerſaries may heare their doome from Gods owne mouth: <hi>This is the worst of all vnder the ſunne, that the ſame things happen alike vnto all, to the good, and to the impious. Hence the hartes of the ſonnes of men, are filled with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and contempt in their lyfe-time, and afterward they shalbe carryed into Hell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Comfort, by compariſon with our Aduerſaryes, and Gods cleere Iudgments agaynſt them.</head>
            <p>BEfore I beginne to diſcourſe of this Argument, I muſt heere meete with an Obiection, which I know will be made agaynſt what hath byn ſayd; to wit, If miſchances happen alyke to the good and to the bad, to the Chriſtian and to the Infidell, to the Catholike and to the Heretike, Why doth <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine</hi> make <hi>Temporall felicity</hi> a Marke,<note place="margin">De Eccleſ. l. 2. c. 20.</note> wherby to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the true Chriſtian Church? I anſwere, that without all doubt there is a kind of Temporall felicity proper vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the true Church, according to the prediction of the Prophets that haue ſpoken ſo much of the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and happines therof. This felicity (though the ſame be mingled with many priuate miſchances) is apparant, and may be diſcerned from the felicity of prophane world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21611:13"/> by three notes, by the <hi>Authour,</hi> by the <hi>End,</hi> by the <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> therof. The Authour of this felicity is God, not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king according to the ordinary courſe of things, but by miracle, ſending the ſame downe from heauen. And therfore it is tearmed by <hi>Bellarmine, Diuinitùs data,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 5: de ciuit. c. 46.</note> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally giuen of God; and by <hi>S. Augustine, A Deo euidentiſsima largitate conceſſa,</hi> comming apparently from the ſpeciall bounty of God. This felicity God vſeth to grant when the ſame is neceſſary for the defence of true Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Infidelity and Hereſy: and it appeared manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the victories obtayned by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the great, by <hi>Honorius</hi> his Sonne, by <hi>Charles</hi> alſo the great. Neyther hath the like ſpeciall prouidence and ſupernaturall aſſiſtance been wanting or leſſe apparant in ſundry battayles fought in this age betwixt Catholiks and Heretikes. For though God permit ſtrange accidents ſometymes, which tend to particular triall of his ſeruants, yet misfortunes and miraculous ouerthrowes, diſmall &amp; vnfortunate deaths fall more frequently vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his enemies, as might be proued by examples ten for one, if need ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.<note place="margin">Lib. 5. de ciuit. c. 18.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> (ſayth S. Auguſtine) <hi>that men might not thinke that the proſperity of this life, were not to be gotten but by ſeruing the Diuell, adorned the two moſt Chriſtian Emperours Conſtantine and Theodoſius, with all kind of worldly felicity the hart of man could wish: On the other ſide that Christians might know that they are not to ſerue God for theſe temporall goods, he would haue the raigne of Iouian a moſt pious Emperour more short, then that of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian the Apoſtata. Alſo Graetian a godly Prince</hi> (not ſo gracious in name, as in manners) <hi>he permitted vnto the ſword of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Tyrant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly this felicity the Marke of the Church, is knowne by the <hi>End,</hi> which is the ſaluation of ſoules, by dilatation of Chriſtian Religion amongſt <hi>Heathens,</hi> and by maintenance of peace &amp; vnity in the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church agaynſt the breaches of factious doctrine. For without queſtion, Felicity that ſerues to ſo diuine &amp; heauenly an <hi>end,</hi> is diuine and heauenly, and ſheweth the Church, in fauour wherof the ſame is granted, to be the only true
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21611:14"/> Chriſtian Church. Neyther it is hard for any man to diſcerne vnto which Church this felicity, mantayning peace of Religion amongſt Chriſtians, &amp; dilating Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion among the <hi>Heathens,</hi> doth belonge: as alſo where that accurſed kind of felicity is found, by which no Nation of Infidells hath been conuerted, but only the quiet of Chriſtendome, in matters aſwell of Religion, as of ciuill Gouernement, peruerted.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this felicity proper vnto the Church, is made euident by the <hi>Effect,</hi> to wit, by the pious workes &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liberalityes therof, ſhining in the Princes vnto whome the ſame is granted. For as God doth by ſpeciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, honour and enrich theſe Princes for the benefit of his Church; ſo likewiſe by ſecret inſpiration, he doth infuſe acknowledgment heerof into their hart, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them to diſcharge their debt of gratitude towardes him, by ſhewing their liberalityes vnto his Church. Thus <hi>Cyrus</hi> though a Pagan did acknowledge his temporall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity in being made Monarch of the world from the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the God of Iſrael,<note place="margin">2. Paralip. c. 36. v. 23.</note> for the comfort of his baniſhed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; whome therfore he ſet at liberty, reſtored vnto their country, and aſſiſted them both with his authority and liberality to rebuild their Temple. Who doth not know the reuerence vnto the Church, the obedience vnto Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, the magnificent bounty of erecting euery where Temples vnto Chriſt that ſhined in the moſt mighty and fortunate Chriſtian Emperours, as were <hi>Conſtantine, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius,</hi> and <hi>Charls,</hi> all three ſurnamed the Great? Who doth not ſee the workes of true Chriſtian felicity in our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and of what Religion thoſe Princes were, by whom Churches, Monaſteryes, Hoſpitalls, and other workes of Piety, with their temporall endowments were foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
            <p>This then is that kind of <hi>Temporall felicity,</hi> which is to be held <hi>a Marke of the Church,</hi> to wit, <hi>That,</hi> wherof Gods miraculous prouidence, is the <hi>Authour,</hi> Propagation of Chriſtianity amongſt <hi>Heathens,</hi> the <hi>end,</hi> Liberalityes in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral workes of Piety, the <hi>effect.</hi> Without theſe reſpects,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21611:14"/> to make happy Euent a note of the truth, or vnlucky ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe a ſigne of falſhood, what is it, but to ſet Religion on the dyce, to expoſe Conſcience vnto chaunce, to make Fayth mutable with the wind? If the Profeſſors of true Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, caſt out of Churches, by the piety of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors built, meete to heare Gods word in a priuate cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>shall Truth that remaynes for euer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Veritas Domini maner in aeternum. Pſal. 136.</note> ſtand obnoxious vnto the rottenes of the roome? muſt their fayth alſo fall to the ground and periſh with their bodyes, if happily the place breake through the weight of the multitudes that thither ouer-zealouſly flocke? Deſire of the food of their ſoule, ſo drawing away their thoughts, as they did not afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand apprehend the daunger of their corporall life? God forbid.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Progidious thinges that did happen at the change from Catholike Religion in England.</head>
               <p>VVIll our Aduerſaries themſelues be content to haue their Religion put to this triall? If they be content, things in this kind recorded by their Annales, will bring their cauſe in danger. When King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight had withdrawne himſelf from the obedience of the Sea of Rome, togeather with Schiſme (though agaynſt his will) did enter Irreligion towards the moſt bleſſed Sacrament reſerued in Churches, what happened?<note place="margin">Stow, or Howes cronicle.</note> they ſhall vnderſtand in their owne Croniclers wordes. <hi>Vpon the</hi> 25. <hi>of May, the rood of S. Margarets Patins by the Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>street in London was pulled downe and broken in peeces togeather with the Tabernacle. And three nights after, to wit on the</hi> 27. <hi>of May, was a great fire in the ſame S. Margarets Parish not farre from the Church, the which flre conſumed there more then a dozen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouſes, and many perſons, men and women brent to death.</hi> Was not this a iudgment? did not God preſently puniſh that fact of Hereſy with fire, the puniſhment by Chriſtian cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome appoynted for that kind of impiety? Did not the fire come iuſt in time to puniſh that irreligious act, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21611:15"/> giuen them firſt three dayes to repent, according to that decree of the Scripture,<note place="margin">Eſd. 10. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>He that within three dayes shall not come backe to Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his whole ſubstance shall be conſumed?</hi> Did not the fire fall right in the place where the ſin was committed, as if God by ſending that fire had ſayd vnto them, you haue diſquieted my Tabernacle, violated my houſe, abuſed my ſacred Body left you vnder the forme of bread, and would not repent: therfore in vengeance therof, I now burne your tabernacles, fire your houſes, conſume your bodyes into aſhes.</p>
               <p>When Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the ſecond yeare of her reigne, had put Catholiks from all Churches, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them ſo much as one for the Religion that all her Chriſtian Progenitours Kings of England had profeſſed: who knowes not what happened vnto the Chiefe, the moſt goodly and glorious of all thoſe Churches, preſently vpon the very next yeare, their Religion being ſcarſe yet warme in the profeſſion thereof?<note place="margin">An. Reg. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>On the fourth of Iune</hi> (ſayth the ſame Annaliſt) <hi>betweene foure and fiue of the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, the steeple of Paules in London was fired by lightening. The fire braſt forth (as it ſeemed to the beholders) two or three yardes beneath the foote of the Croſse, and from thence, brent the ſpeere (which was of two hundred and ſixty foote) downe to the stone-worke and bells, ſo terribly that within the ſpace of foure houres the ſame steeple with the roofe of the Church ſo much as was timber or otherwiſe combustible, were conſumed, which was a lamentable ſight, and pittifull remembrance to the beholders therof.</hi> Thus he. This was the welcome Heauen gaue vnto the new Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion then entring into our Kingdome, by fiering vpon them that moſt magnificent Temple, which vnder Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes had ſtood almoſt a thouſand yeares. They that vrge the falling of an old chamber as miraculous ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance ſent from heauen vpon Catholike Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: what can they with any ſhew of probability anſwere vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that will preſſe them with this prodigious lightening &amp; fiering which came directly from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon them? Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing therwith their Communion-table was alſo fired, though their Cronicler, to ſaue the credit of their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21611:15"/> Ghoſpell make no mention therof? Neyther is it without myſtery, that <hi>this fire brake forth from vnder the foote of the Croſſe,</hi> as comming agaynſt the enemyes of the ſigne of the Croſſe, and to ſhew Gods anger agaynſt them for their contempt of that moſt holy inſtrument of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>What will they ſay vnto another Prodigy alſo ſet downe in their Annals, that vpon the tyme their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was begotten by Q <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and chriſtened in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland? Iuſt at the ſame tyme ſo many monſtruous births happened within two or three moneths, as the like is not noted in any of our antiquityes. <hi>This yeare</hi> (ſayth the ſayd M. Stow) <hi>were many monſtruous births. In march a mare brought forth a foale with one body and two heades, and as it were a long tayle, growing betweene the two heades: alſo a Sow farrowed a pig with foure leggs, like to the armes of a man-child with handes and fingers &amp;c. In April a Sow farrowed a pig with two bodyes, eight feete, and but one head. Many calues and lambes were monſtruous, ſome with collars of skins growing about their neckes like to the dubble ruffes of shirts and neckercheffs then vſed. On the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith of May, a man-child was borne at Chichester in Suſſex, the head armes and legges wherof were like an anatomy, the breast and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly monſtrous bigge, from the nauill, as it were a longe ſtringe was hanging, about the necke a great collar of flesh and skinne like to the ruffe of a shirt, comming vp aboue the eares playting and folding.</hi> Thus he. Was it by chance (thinke you) that ſo many monſtruous and vgly <hi>Births</hi> happened thus on a heap to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with the birth of your Ghoſpell? or rather were they not ſent by Gods prouidence, to lay before eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your carnall eyes, the fedity and deformity of your change from the fayth of all your Chriſtian Aunceſtors?</p>
               <p>I will heere conclude without paſſing into forrayne countryes, only I will intreate our Aduerſaries to looke out of England no further then they may almoſt from thence reach with their corporall ſight, to wit, vnto the <hi>Hill</hi> on the <hi>Sea-shoare</hi> neere vnto <hi>Deepe.</hi> There the rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of one of their Temples are yet to be ſeen, which fell vpon their reformed Puritan Auditory, at the tyme of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21611:16"/> Preach, wherwith foure hundred with the Miniſter were oppreſſed. The cauſe of this ouerthrow was not vulgar and ordinary as in our caſe, but a ſtrange and terrible whirle-winde, rayſed and ſent by Gods ſpeciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to puniſh them. The remembrance of this whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind and wofull accident will happily take from them their inſulting ſpirit, or at leaſt ſo blow away their vayne and friuolous clamors, that this accident was Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpon vs for our Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they will not be heard with eſteeme by any man of iudgment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The death of the Catholike Preacher of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, compared with the death of <hi>Caluin</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt they thinke we ſhall not find amongſt their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, any that was ſtroken with ſo ſuddayne and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtrous a death as the Ieſuite Preacher of this Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was. This ſhews how ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they are of their owne Church, and how like the <hi>Lamiae,</hi> of whome <hi>Plutarch</hi> writes, that being at home they pull their eyes out of their head,<note place="margin">Luther. tom. 7. Witte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. fol. 230. a. poſt medium. Conradus Schluſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg. in Theolog. Caluin. l. 2. fol. 72.</note> and locke them vp in coffers, and they only vſe them, when they are diſpoſed to goe abroad to viſit their Neighbours. Doth not <hi>Luther</hi> write, that their great Grand-ſire <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampadius</hi> was killed in his bedde, ſhaken with horrible frights, the Diuell appearing to him, and this in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his errour agaynſt the Sacrament? Doth not a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Proteſtant Super-intendent giue this teſtimony of the death of the Puritans Dad <hi>Iohn Caluin? God (ſayth he) in the rod of his fury punished Caluin before the dreadfull houre of his vnhappy death with his mighty hand. For being in deſpayre and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon the Diuell he gaue vp his wicked ſoule, ſwearing, curſing &amp; blaſpheming. He dyed on the diſeaſe of lice and wormes, increaſing in a most loath-ſome vlcer about his priuy partes, ſo as none preſent could endure the ſtench.</hi> Theſe be the wordes of that Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21611:16"/>
               <p>But becauſe this happend within the walls of <hi>Geneua,</hi> and in <hi>Caluins priuy Chamber,</hi> we cannot haue ſuch proofe therof, but Puritans will outface both Proteſtants and vs. Wherfore we will bringe them out of the walls of <hi>Geneua</hi> into the open field, out of <hi>Caluins</hi> cloſet into the ſight of heauen and earth,<note place="margin">Iuell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy. pag. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. Oſiander in Epitom hiſt. Eccl. Cent. 16. pag. 203. Gualt. Apol. fol. 30. a. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe finem obijt in bello Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inglius, &amp; Armatus obijt.</note> vnto a ſpectacle wherof two whole armyes were witneſſes. Behold <hi>Hulderick Zuinglius</hi> whom they honour as a Prophet ioyned in commiſſion with <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to preach the eternall Ghoſpell, as an excellent man ſent of God to giue light vnto the whole world, in the midst of darknes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truth was vnknowne and vnheard off.</hi> This Miniſter or rather Patriarke of the Miniſtry, as themſelues confeſſe, <hi>hauing ſought by famine to oppreſſe fiue Catholicke townes, and force them by want of victuals to conſent vnto his doctrine,</hi> when they ſtood in their defence, <hi>came armed into the field,</hi> where hauing firſt embrued his ſword in much Chriſtian bloud, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe togeather <hi>with fiue other Militant Miniſters,</hi> was ſlayne in the battayle.</p>
               <p>I deſire the Chriſtian to compare togeather theſe two deaths, the one of <hi>Robert Drury</hi> that dyed preaching by this laſt accident: The other of the Reformitan <hi>Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius</hi> which I haue ſet downe out of their owne recordes. This done then in the ſight of that God <hi>that hateth iniquity and loueth charity,</hi> let him define which of the two deaths be iudgeth moſt Chriſtian and happy, or with which of the two Preachers he would rather wiſh his ſoule.<note place="margin">Lutherani apud Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Apol. fol. 8. a initio. Gladium à Chriſto prohibitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corripuit Gladius Spiritus, quod eſt verbum Dei. Eph. 4.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius</hi> the Patriarke of Puritans &amp; Miniſters dyed as he was pranſing on his warlike palfrey with his piſtoll at his ſide and launce in his hande. This Father of the Society of Ieſus, ſitting in a chayre, the ſeate and enſigne of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall authority to preach, clothed with ſuch Prieſtly ornaments as the Church doth preſcribe, for the more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent performance of that office. The one with a <hi>ſworde in his hand,</hi> ſtretching forth his arme to ſpill Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bloud: the other with the <hi>ſword of Gods holy truth</hi> in his mouth, the enemy only of ſinne and vice, ſpreading abroad his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, to gather into the boſome of God and his Church, ſoules redeemed with Chriſt his moſt precious bloud.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21611:17"/> The one <hi>exhorting both by word and example</hi> his armed audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,<note place="margin">Noui &amp; exquiſitiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris fax. &amp; auctor. Oſiand. vbi ſupra.</note> to reuenge, to murder, to maſſacre: The other (<note n="*" place="margin">His text was, ſerue nequam omne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum dimiſi tibi &amp;c. Superbia, &amp; crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſus. Oſiand. Epitom. hiſt. fol. 30 Qui ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate in Deo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. 1. Io. 4.16. Qui non diligit manet in morre. 1. Io. 3.15. Valerius Max. l. 4. c. 4. Daniel. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for that was the ſubiect his ſermon) preching the <hi>Precept of charity,</hi> perſwading his deuout Auditours to loue their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes, to forgiue iniuryes, to roote reuenge and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour cleane out of their hart. <hi>From the eyes of one ſparkled fire of anger and Martiall fury,</hi> not to be quenched but with the bloud of his enemyes; From the eyes of the other ſprunge teares of <hi>Deuotion</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> which by Sympathy cauſed waters of Contrition in the harts of his hearers, which flowing out at their eyes, might ſerue as a <hi>ſecond Baptiſme,</hi> to waſh their ſoules pure in that moment of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and death.</p>
               <p>Is there any man ſo voyd of Chriſtianity that will not preferre this <hi>death in charity, and therfore in God,</hi> before that death of hatred and reuenge, and therfore a death not of body only, but euen of ſoule? Oh that the Spirit of God with the gale of his aſpiring Grace, would driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the cloudes of human ſorrow that ouer-whelme the harts of fleſh and bloud, that pure Chriſtian Fayth, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in her proper brightnes, might giue ſentence of the quality of this accident! Then we would not ſoe much pitty, as enuy ſuch happy paſſages out of this life, nor tearme them <hi>diſaſtrous,</hi> but rather (if I may ſo ſpeake) <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struous</hi> deaths. For (that I may apply the wordes of a prophane Authour vnto a true ſubiect) <hi>Non ita homines ex ſpirant, ſed Astra ſedes ſuas repetunt.</hi> Theſe be deaths by which men fall not to the ground, but STARRES returne vnto their heauenly home: <hi>thoſe starres</hi> I meane, wherof <hi>Daniel</hi> ſayth, <hi>They that informe men vnto righteouſnes, shall shine as STARRES in the firmament for all eternity.</hi> Certainly his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fell not ſo faſt to the ground, but his ſoule flew vp as faſt vnto heauen, like the <hi>Doue</hi> into <hi>Noe</hi> his Arke, with the branch of Oliue, the Word of Peace and Charity in mouth. King <hi>Euander</hi> in the vntimely death of his only ſonne, tooke comfort to conſider he dyed in a glorious enterprize of human friendſhip, in the conducting of his exiled friends into theit promiſed Country of reſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21611:17"/> that he would euer ioy in the memory of that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall death, —
<q>Ducentem in Latium Teucros, cecidiſſe iuuabit.</q>
               </p>
               <p>What greater, or more glorious endeauour of Diuine Charity, then to guide ſoules made to Gods image into the felicity of their ceceſtiall Country, that is, the bliſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full viſion of the face of their Creatour? Seing it was Gods holy pleaſure to take them out of the world, whoſe longer liues in our iudgment would haue byn beneficiall vnto his Church; though we cannot but feele their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature death, yet we cannot alſo but ioy in this happy circumſtance therof, that they dyed in the exerciſe of the higheſt act of Chriſtian Mercy; that their laſt breath was, in calling men vnto God, moſt bleſſedly ſpent, that the ſweat of death they felt, was no other, but the ſweat of burning charity towardes God and man, —
<q>Ducentem ad caelos animas, cecidiſſe iuuabit.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here we may with reaſon take into our mouth King <hi>Dauid</hi> his funerall ſonge in prayſe of <hi>Abner, As the ſlouthfull vſe to dy, thou didſt not dye, O Abner:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Reg. 2.3</note> not groning &amp; breathing forth thy ſoule and ſpirit in bed, but thundering and breathing forth Gods holy Word and ſpirit in pulpit. <hi>Thyne handes were not bound,</hi> but ſtill mouing in charitable deedes, ſo long as they had motion of life. <hi>Thy feete were not put into fetters,</hi> but free; and that of them particularly the Prophet may ſeeme to haue ſpoken,<note place="margin">Iſa. 52.7.</note> 
                  <hi>How beautifull are the feete of him that doth preach Peace, that doth denounce the best things!</hi> For what thing better then charity &amp; loue? <hi>as men fall before the ſonnes of iniquity, ſo thou falleſt,</hi> a Martyr in the ſight of God &amp; his Angels, though the perſecutor appeared not in the ſight of men. What ſhall I ſay more? I will conclude with the words of our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Matth. 24.45.</note> ſo proper to ſet forth the happines of this death, as I ſhall not need to adde ſo much as a word by way of application. <hi>Who is the faythfull and prudent ſeruant whom his Lord hath put ouer his family to giue them MEATE in tyme?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Non in pane ſed in VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BO.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed that ſeruant whom his Master coming shall finde SO DOING. Verily I ſay vnto you, he will place him ouer all his goodes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21611:18"/>
               <head>Proteſtants that were preſent at this Sermon defended.</head>
               <p>SOme vrge this accident as a iudgment of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, not ſo much agaynſt Catholikes as agaynſt Proteſtants, that hauing preachers of their owne, would reſort vnto this Catholike Sermon, whom I will refell briefly, not by way of Rhetoricall diſcourſe, but by way of Syllogiſme, prouing by their owne principles theſe fower enſuing propoſitions, vnanſwerably.</p>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The firſt Propoſition.</hi> Proteſtants by the Law of God, may heare Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Sermons.</head>
                  <p>THis is proued. Becauſe Proteſtants may heare the Miniſters of Gods holy Worde, that haue Diuine Order, Diuine calling, Diuine Commiſſion to preach it. For whom may they heare, if they may not heare them whom God appoynts? But the Prieſts of the Roman Church haue Diuine Order, Diuine Calling, Diuine Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to preach Gods holy Word, as now Proteſtants, &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Luther</hi> did, who ſayth, <hi>The Papists haue the TRVE office of Preaching,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In Papatu eſt VE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RVM prudican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di officiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Luth. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Anabapt. Maſon his booke of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> acknowledge with full conſent: yea they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and contend to haue a Diuine Order, Calling, and Commiſſion to preach and adminiſter Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, by the Tradition of our Church, from handes of Catholike Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, originally from the Pope. Therfore Proteſtants by the law of God, may heare the Sermons of Catholike Prieſts, at the leaſt with the ſame <hi>prouiſo,</hi> wherwith they heare their own, to approue what they find to agree with Scripture, and reproue what they find preached agaynſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21611:18"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond Propoſition.</hi> Proteſtants should rather heare Catholike Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, then Puritan.</head>
                  <p>THis is proued. Becauſe wiſedome teacheth, that in doubtfull Queſtions we chooſe the ſureſt ſide, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in affayres that concerne the euerlaſting ſaluation of our ſoules. Wherfore in this queſtion, whether Catholik or Purita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Preachers are to be heard, we muſt rather chooſe the certaineſt part. But that Catholike Prieſts are the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God, endued with Diuine Order and authority to preach his Word, and conſequently the Men who by Diuine Ordination are to be heard, is moſt ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne: becauſe all agree therin; in ſo much as Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts as I ſayd, chaleng their Orders from the Roman, that if the Roman ordination be not currant,<note place="margin">M. Bridges defence of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern pag. 1276.</note> much leſſe can theirs be currant, as ſayth the Proteſtant Biſhop of <hi>Oxford: If the Roman Priests be not Ministers, then are not we Ministers at all, for we are Ministers of thoſe Ministers.</hi> Therfore out of the principles of Chriſtian wiſedome, men ſhould rather heare Catholike, then Puritan Preachers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third Propoſition.</hi> Proteſtants by the principles of their Religion,<note place="margin">See Iohn White his way, pag. 126. Euery particular man muſt iudge of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</note> are bound to heare Catholike Sermons.</head>
                  <p>THis I proue: becauſe the Iudge is bound by the law of God and man, and light of reaſon to heare both partyes before be giue ſentence for, or agaynſt eyther, and to condemne eyther ſide vnheard is intolerable wronge: <hi>But euery particular Proteſtant, and euery one of the common people is a iudge appoynted of God, hauing the publick authority of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſpeaking openly vnto all in Scripture,</hi> wherby he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21611:19"/> 
                     <hi>the greatest and moſt Catholike Church in the world,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">No priuat iudgment but the publicke cenſure. A priuate man may find fault with the beſt Church. pag. 128.</note> to wit, the Roman, and may find a fault in <hi>the best Church in the world,</hi> to wit, the Proteſtant, as themſelues moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly teach; auerring that <hi>this doctrine was neuer denyed by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Church, but the Roman, that knowing her doctrine to be droſſe, durst not put herſelf to this triall.</hi> Therfore euery particular and priuate Proteſtant is bound by the law of God, and Man, Grace and Reaſon, to heare the Roman Church, as well as the Proteſtant.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fourth Propoſition.</hi> They that heare not our Sermons, but condemne vs vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truſt of their Miniſters, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſaued.</head>
                  <p>THis I proue. Becauſe they that built vpon the truſt and credit of the Proteſtant Church, and paſſe not to the triall that they may ſay of their certayne knowledg this is errour, this is truth, theſe cannot be ſaued. This is cleere, becauſe none <hi>is ſaued without diuine, and ſupernaturall most certayne Fayth:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sine Fide impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile place<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Deo. Heb. 11.6. Field in his Appe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix p. 2. p. 18.</note> but Proteſtants themſelues acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that Fayth built vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the authority of their Church, is but humane, acquiſite, and fallible, ſeeing the ſame may erre: therfore, they that build vpon the truſt and credit of their Church cannot be ſaued. But they that heare not the Roman Church, condemne her only vpon the truſt and credit of the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſay vpon their own knowledge that this, or that is her doctrine, nor conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that ſhe is in errour: Therfore except they heare the Catholike Church her ſermons (if they can) that they may ſay of their owne knowledge her doctrines are erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous and theirs the truth,<note place="margin">Euery particular man muſt Try all things. Iohn Whites way p. 126.</note> they cannot be ſaued. For how can they be ſaued except they comply with that Precept, <hi>Try all, and hold the best:</hi> this Precept as Proteſtants teach being <hi>Diuine,</hi> and ſuch a one as doth concerne <hi>euery priuat man?</hi> Is not the Roman Religion one amongſt all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions that are to be tryed, yea the <hi>only one,</hi> amongſt them all? How then can they be ſaued that will not try the Roman among the reſt, that not vpon truſt, but by their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21611:19"/> owne triall they may know whether her Doctrine is to be held? Wherfore they that reprehend thoſe Proteſtants for comming to this Sermon are ignorant, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the firſt principles of their owne Fayth.</p>
                  <p>Hence I inferre, that our Aduerſaries cannot eſteeme of this Accident as a puniſhment of God, if without paſſion they will pronounce ſentence by the principles of their owne Religion, ſuppoſing (which is moſt certayne) that the ſubiect of the ſermon was the duty of Charity to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue each other, &amp; to be ready to giue account vnto God whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are called out of the world. For what was there in that Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God may be thought to haue puniſhed by that fall, the Doctrine preached &amp; the order to preach it, being both his owne? If this miſchance ought to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as a token of Gods vengeance agaynſt the doctrine of the Ieſuits, ſurely God was ſingularly offended with that doctrine the Ieſuit did actually preach at that very inſtant, when by the fall his breath was ſtopped, which was the doctrine of Charity and Peace. O heauenly do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and O happy breath that is loſt in the preaching therof! which was the laſt ſermon and Cygnaean ſonge as of this Father of the Society of Ieſus,<note place="margin">Hier. in ep. ad Gal. l. 3. c. 6.</note> ſo likewiſe of the Diſciple beloued of Ieſus, whoſe life ended, whoſe breath expired in breathing forth this doctrine, <hi>Loue ech other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence alſo appeares the vanity of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue found this farre fecht argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t agaynſt vs. This accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſay they, happened vpon the Papiſts on the fifth of Nouember, <hi>ſtilo nouo,</hi> therefore it was a puniſhment of the Treaſon they intended agaynſt vs on the 5. of Nouember <hi>stilo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri.</hi> Firſt this their arguing is folly, becauſe in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon or congruence, agaynſt the rules of Logick<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they do <hi>tranſire degenere ad genus,</hi> that is, compare things togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of different kindes, <hi>stilo nouo, &amp; ſtilo veteri,</hi> being diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent kindes of computation. So that if we take the thing according to the truth, and not according to the ſound of words, the 5. of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber <hi>ſtilo veteri,</hi> is not the 5. but the 15. of noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber <hi>stilo nouo.</hi> Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly agaynſt this vanity grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> words without ſenſe we haue an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t inuincible
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21611:20"/> deriued from the firſt principles of Chriſtianity, to wit, that God being iuſt, cannot puniſh men for ſinnes they neuer committed, but euer deteſted. Now theſe that fell at this Sermon, neuer intended that gunpowder-treaſon (as theſe accuſers bely them) nor euer thought therof but with deteſtation and terrour. Therfore certainly God being holy &amp; iuſt, did not intend this accident to puniſh that ſinne vpon them. Finally what ſenſe or congruence is there in this prouidence, for that a ſinne commited a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Chriſtian Charity, many yeares agoe, God ſhould now puniſh men altogeather innocent therof: and this in the act of preaching Chriſtian Charity, agaynſt rancour and malice, which doctrine of all other, is oppoſite vnto ſuch execrable vndertakings?</p>
                  <p>Some perchance will ſay, that though he preached Charity, yet he preached in the Popiſh faſhion, that by deedes of charity they merit heauen. I do not know if he made mention of merit;<note place="margin">De Ciuit. l. 2. c. 29. Caſta celebrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, vbi audiant quàm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ad te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus viue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re debea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vt beató ſemper<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> viuere merean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> ſuppoſe he did: Is the ſermon and meeting to be cenſured in this reſpect? Let theſe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers receaue their doome by the mouth of S. <hi>Augustine. They be</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>impious, they are vngratefull vnto God, they are deepely oppreſſed by the wicked ſpirit, who murmure agaynst the chaſt celebrity of ſuch meetings, where men are taught, how they are to liue well for the time in this preſent world, that ſo they may ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIT to liue bleſſedly for euer in the next world.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Comfort, from the Ends and Intentions of God in this Accident, wherof we may make Profit.</head>
            <p>IF the Doctrine preached was ſo pious, and the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher authorized to preach by Diuine Order, why was the ſermon ouerthrowne by ſuddayne death, in the mid'ſt therof? Why? Becauſe God is Lord, he may permit, he may doe as he pleaſeth, and yet <hi>no man
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21611:20"/> may ſay vnto him, Why do'ſt thou ſo?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Propter fines no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, Deo notiffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos, in die Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randos. Auguſt.</note> He will not haue man thinke he hath right to be of his priuy Councell, nor in his doings to reprehend what he doth not comprehend. Notwithſtanding why this miſchance fell on theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons rather then on others, is a myſtery that lyes hidden with a million of more in the treaſury of Gods ſecrets, to be reuealed at the day of Iudgment: yet in generall why this ſame was permitted in ſome Catholikes, reaſons may be rendered, by which we may reape both comfort and profit.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons in regard of Protestants.</head>
               <p>VVIll Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts haue a reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why God would haue this Ieſuit dye before their eyes, preaching forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenes of iniuryes, charity and peace, that they might be witneſſes of the fight agaynſt the vulgar Puritan ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, that Ieſuits incenſe Catholike people agaynſt them, vnto bloud-ſhed and murder? Behold a Martyr, a witneſſe that loſt his breath in the refutation of this ſlaunder: Nor can their accuſers name the Ieſuit, that for the time he was Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, killed any man, or euer drew ſword in anger, or we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t armed into the field. They be preſent indeed many tymes in battayle to help the ſoules that are wounded, and can make vſe of their helpe: and though they walke in the mid'ſt of dangers, yet haue they no other armour, then their habit, no other piſtoll but their beades by their ſide,<note place="margin">Iniquiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus belli Author. Oſiander Hiſt. Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 16. fol. 30.</note> no other ſword and lance, beſides a Croſſe in the one hand, and their Breuiary in the other. How would Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans inſult, and traduce Ieſuits as manquellers, could they proue one of them to haue dyed as did their Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> with his fiue Martiall Mates, fighting in the field vnto death, drowned lyke <hi>Pharao</hi> in the red ſea of bloud, of the effuſion wherof himſelfe was Author?<note place="margin">In hoc co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſcent homines quòd diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipuli m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtis. Ioa. 14, 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Will they haue a reaſon? God would haue this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Prieſt dye in the commendation of Charity, then which no doctrine is more properly Chriſtian, that they might feele euen with their handes, the raſhnes of them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21611:21"/> that iudged the fall was to puniſh the then preaching of Doctrine <hi>Antichristian.</hi> They iudged (being ignorant of the Catholike cuſtome) that our Miniſters of Gods holy Word be like theirs, who commonly ſpend the time, not in exhortations vnto good life, but in bitter declamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s agaynſt the Pope. This accident hath made knowne our Sermons to be made in another Tune, as oppoſite vnto theirs, as is light vnto darknes, ſweetnes vnto bitternes, Charity vnto hatred, mildnes vnto arrogancy.</p>
               <p>Will they haue yet another reaſon? God permitted this accident, that the zeale of hearing Gods word, &amp; the hard condition of Catholikes might heereby be made knowne vnto the Chriſtian world. All the Churches of England haue byn erected by our Catholike Anceſtours, and yet Catholikes now haue not permitted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much as one Church of ſo many, to heare the word of that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Fayth, wherby the ſame were founded. They muſt eyther want the comfort of the <hi>bread of life,</hi> or els reſort to priuate Chambers for the ſame with danger of miſchance; that the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſe of <hi>Ieremy</hi> his complaint may ſeeme renewed in vs,<note place="margin">Thren. c. 5. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>In animabus nostris afferebamus nobis panem:</hi> With loſſe of our liues we get the bread of our ſoules. And which is worſe, when ſuch diſaſters happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they that haue taken our Churches from vs, inſult agaynſt vs, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that built them.</p>
               <p>We may yet adde hereunto a fourth Reaſon. Seeing God in his iudgments ſtill aymeth at the finall end of his mercyes, why may we not thinke he permitted this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to mitigate men harts towards Catholike Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Diſponit omnia ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auiter.</note> cauſing, according to his ſweet courſe of prouidence, the inſtinct of nature to concurre heerin with the motion of Grace? For ſuch is the diſpoſition of mankind, that the moſt Innocent being in exceſſe of proſperity, are enuyed, their great vertues ſuppreſſed, ſmall faults eagerly purſued to their diſgrace. On the other ſide, when men are fallen from the higheſt of felicity into the depth of miſery, euen the wicked'ſt are pittyed, their faultines extenuated, and what may be in them worthy of prayſe, is preſently called
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21611:21"/> to mind. <hi>Iehu</hi> when he ſaw <hi>Ieſabel</hi> ſtand in her window, looking proudly &amp; wantonly into the ſtreete,<note place="margin">4. 10</note> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her to be caſt downe. When ſhe was dead and her body lay bleeding in the way, her knowne imme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes could not hinder his hart from a compaſſionate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of her worth, ſaying, <hi>She was a Queene,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sepelite eam qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> filia Regis eſt. v. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>and a Kings daughter, let her be buried with honour.</hi> Who knowes not the weeping of <hi>Alexander</hi> at the death of <hi>Darius?</hi> The teares of <hi>Caeſar</hi> vpon the fight of <hi>Pompey</hi> his head, through reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his former high worthines and ſtate? The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers of Hieruſalem, as <hi>Ieremy</hi> foretold,<note place="margin">Ioſephus de bello Iudaico. Herem. 2. 15.</note> wept in her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; yea the Emperour that was Gods inſtrument therein, paſſing afterward by occaſion that way, ſhed many teares vpon her, <hi>This is Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that was once the fayre and beautifull Citty, the ioy of the whole earth.</hi> If miſery be thus able to purchaſe fauour vnto wicked perſons and mortall enemyes, how much more vnto Catholike Religion that in ſo many of her children, ſlayne in that their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent exerciſe of deuotion, lay ſo wofull a ſpectacle to our Country? It is ſcarſe poſſible, but by that pittifull ſight, men ſhould be warned to remember her Sanctity, her Dignity, her ineſtimable Benefits in former tymes beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed on this Land; and in their hearts to ſay: This is the <hi>Religion,</hi> that, from <hi>her Head-Citty Rome,</hi> ſent hither <hi>Christia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> Preachers,<note place="margin">Beda hiſt. Angl. Tob. 13.22 Per vicos Alleluia ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tabitur. Angloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gens quae nihil no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerat niſi Barbaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frendere, nunc Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braeum didicit Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluia ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare. Greg.</note> wherby we <hi>Englishmen</hi> were firſt conuerted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Idolatry vnto Chriſt, and by the merits of his Bloud wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from the crimes of our cruelty, <hi>in the heauenly lauer of Purity.</hi> This is the <hi>Religion</hi> that did firſt baniſh from our mouth the vncouth names of <hi>Panime</hi> Gods; that taught vs firſt to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the <hi>ſauing</hi> Name of IESVS; by whoſe meanes the ſweet <hi>Alleluia</hi> began firſt to be <hi>ſonge in our streetes,</hi> in hope of heauenly felicity. This is the Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that for a thouſand yeares togeather was the ſole Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Queene raigning in all our Catholike Princes, working in their harts knowledge and loue of celeſtiall things, &amp; mouing their handes to leaue monuments of their piety, memorialls of their charity, religious exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of ſanctity, to the ioy of heauen and wonder of earth. Theſe cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21611:22"/> of truth, and the like are both eaſy and obuious to be had of any that will not ſhut their eyes agaynſt them,<note place="margin">Spera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia. Heb. 11.1. Granum frumenti cadens in te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ram. mortuum. Io. 22.24.</note> &amp; moſt efficacious to moue harts not altogeather deuoyd of humanity. How can Chriſtians be ſo barbarous as to hate that Church, by which they were firſt changed from <hi>Barbariſme vnto Christianity?</hi> Or perſecute and ſeeke to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw that Religion, that is the <hi>only ground and pillar of hope,</hi> that any of their Chriſtian anceſtors were ſaued? We may therfore thinke that God would haue theſe Catholiks as ſo many graynes of wheate, to the end that they might beare <hi>fruite in abundance</hi> fal togeather <hi>in terram bonam &amp; optimam,</hi> vpon the ground of the good,<note place="margin">Luc. 8.15.</note> yea of the beſt natures that are; no nation being (if affection do not deceaue me) more then Engliſh merciful by kind? And ſo we cannot but hope the Catholike Religion, ſo full of ineſtimable worth, and of motiues to winne loue, her doctrine being thus ſowed in harts mollified by iuſt compaſſion, will bring forth a ſtock, if not of feruent profeſſion therof, yet at leaſt of more clement diſpoſition towardes them that profeſſe it</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons for Puritans, and the Inhumanity of ſome of them.</head>
               <p>VVIll Puritans haue a reaſon of Gods permitta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce on their behalfe? God permitted it, to the end that by occaſion therof that might happen, wherby they may ſee the rudenes of their Pretented Holy Diſcipline, behold the inhumanity their Hereſy putteth into peoples harts,<note place="margin">Hooker l. 4. Ecc. Polit.</note> and ſo endeauour ſome remedy therof; <hi>Leaſt</hi> (as a learned Proteſtant warnes them) <hi>vnder pretence of rooting out Popery, they bring extreme Barbarity into the Church.</hi> For there did not want a multitude,<note place="margin">Tuleruut lapides Iudaei. Io. 8.58. &amp; 10.31.</note> that not only with <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious</hi> ſpeech, flowing from bitternes abunding in their hart, not only with <hi>durt,</hi> the image of their contaminate ſoule; but euen with <hi>stones,</hi> the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of <hi>Iewish cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> ſet vpon the poore creatures hurt by that fall, preſently
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21611:22"/> as they were taken vp from vnder the ruines and rubbiſh, that ſome Gentlewomen were forced to leaue their coach to ſaue themſelues in a houſe of their Friendes. This was not the fact of Engliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; they are of more noble nature: Nor of Engliſh Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; Hereſy hath not made them ſo wild: but of Puritans, not of the whole Lande,<note place="margin">See their Pamphet tearmed, Somthing</note> nor of all London (let vs excuſe as many as we may) but of one particle of London, which Puritans boaſt to be their ſpeciall Neſt. How behofefull it is, that this people ſo pure in name, rude in manners, were taught the firſt rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſtianity;<note place="margin">Whitak, de Ecc. cont. 2. q. 5. pag. 301. Si quis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, ei pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata non nocere, id omnes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus. Lut. tom. 1. ep. latin. fol. 334. Etiamſi millies in die &amp;c. 1. Ioan. 3. Trabem in oculo tuo habes. Luc. 6.42 Eſt pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ad mortem. 1. Io. 5.15.</note> that the doctrine of good workes and Chriſtian Charity were more frequently preached vnto them; that the fancy of ſole Fayth were ſilenced, to wit, that (if they once belieue) <hi>they neuer ceaſe to be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God and gracious in his ſight, though they commit murder an hundred times a day.</hi> I confeſſe that no circumſtance of this accident doth ſo grieue me to the hart as this; not for any hurt they did therin vnto vs, for the hurt was only to themſelues. They ſhewed themſelues <hi>more dead</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for want of charity, then the other were dead in body for want of life: the Beames that did oppreſſe and buize the bones of Catholikes were not ſo heauy nor ſo deadly, as were <hi>the beames of paſsion and hatred in the eye of theſe miſcreants,</hi> bruyzing and wounding their ſoule <hi>with the ſinne vnto death,</hi> it being better as the holy<note n="*" place="margin">S. Wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſlaus.</note> King of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia ſaid, <hi>to dye an Abel, then to liue a Cayn.</hi> The cauſe of my griefe is, that any in our Country, ſhould be found ſo voyd of common humanity, to the diſcredit of our Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this being done in the eye of the Stranger, whence now it is ſpread abroad, to the horrour of the Chriſtian world.</p>
               <p>For euery Nation vnder the Cope of heauen, both Chriſtian and Heathen, both Ciuill and Barbarous doth by cuſtome pitty, yea reuerence them that are newly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from vnder the death-blow of chaunce. Wherof we may giue three reaſons grounded on the pious inſtinct of nature. The firſt is, becauſe men ſaued from this deadly ſtroake, ſeeme then to beginne to liue, and to be then as it were borne a new. Wherfore nature bidds men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21611:23"/> &amp; welcome the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe into the world: and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, to wit, to ſeeke to ſtop the firſt breathings of this their new life, is the greateſt barbarity that may be. Againſt which, one bitterly but iuſtly inueigheth, as we may read in the Prince of Poets, whoſe inuectiue I could wiſh none of our Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had drawne particularly vpon themſelues.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quod genus hoc hominum? quaeue hac tam barbara morem</l>
                  <l>Permittit Patria? —</l>
               </q>
               <p>What wild me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be theſe? what barbarous cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try is this?</p>
               <q>
                  <l>We being ſau'd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſea, euen from the iawes of death,</l>
                  <l>They riſe agaynſt vs ſtraight, they do not vs permit</l>
                  <l>In quietneſſe to ſet firſt footings on the ground.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bella cient, prima<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> vetant conſistere terra.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon is, becauſe the ſtroake of chance, as it is in truth, ſo is it taken by the inſtinct of nature, as the ſtroake of Gods ſpeciall prouidence, and hand. From this ſtroake they that are ſaued, as they liue by his ſpeciall will and loue towards them, ſo they are regarded of others as things ſacred vnto God,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Cicero Act. 7. in Verrem initio. Veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur ne quem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſſet &amp;c. Viri Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuitae ſurgent in iudicio &amp;c. Matth. 14.</p>
                     <p>Propter iniquitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corripui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Pſ. 38.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                  </note> and by ſpeciall bande of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyed vnto him, that it is a kind of ſacriledge to violate them. An Oratour of Rome (as <hi>Tully</hi> writeth) pleading for the life of a Captayne, that had in the field receaued many dangerous woundes on head and breaſt, ſhewed the ſcarres or markes therof vnto the Iudges, wherwith he moued them not ſo much to pitty, as to religious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of the <hi>Man, that they feared to condemne him to death,</hi> from ſo many dangers wherof he had byn by fortune, that is Gods ſpeciall protection, moſt ſtrangly ſaued. <hi>Theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Iudges in the Day of Iudgment shall condemne the Puritans,</hi> ſeing they being Heathens bare more reuerence vnto the dead &amp; darke ſignes of Diuine Protection in a guilty perſon, then theſe did vnto the freſh tokens of Gods ſpeciall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, in innocent Chriſtian Women.</p>
               <p>The third reaſon is, becauſe the puniſhment of diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous change, is by the inſtinct of Nature accounted the puniſhment of God, as it were taking the execution of Iuſtice immediatly into his owne hand. Hence it is that they, who from the hand of Diuine execution eſcape af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21611:23"/> frighted, wounded and hurt, are to be held as ſet free by Gods ſpeciall warrant, as puniſhed inough, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the equity of his iudgment. Wherefore preſently to ſet vpon them, as deſeruing more puniſhment, is not only iniuſtice and cruelty, but alſo a kind of impiety and condemnation of God, as if he wanted eyther wiſedome to know, or iuſtice to hate, or power to puniſh ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently the grieuouſnes of mans ſinnes.</p>
               <p>We will not ſtand vpon the Deniall, but this chance might be ſent vpon theſe perſons as a puniſhment of God in regard of their leſſer or veniall ſinnes; ſeing euen Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome it ſelfe, the death moſt glorious of all other, may be inflicted as a puniſhment in this kind,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Mach. 6.14.</note> as the <hi>Machabees Martirs</hi> ſayd: <hi>Nos propeccatis nostris ista patimur.</hi> At leaſt they that ſuffer, may &amp; ought to make that accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> counſelleth, <hi>Decet Martyres verecundos eſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyprian. in exort. Martyr.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſupplicia ſua pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis aſcribere, &amp; non ſe de paſsione iactare.</hi> Wherfore theſe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Catholike men and women, ſuppoſing in Chriſtian humility this to haue byn the ſtroake of Gods hande for their ſinnes, how properly might one of them haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the Puritan with the wordes of holy <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 19, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Haue pitty, haue pitty on me, for the hand of God hath ſtrucken me,</hi> for my ſinnes, as you ſuppoſe, and I do not deny; yet the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, &amp; how great or ſmall they are, God knowes much better then you do. Deſerued I puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Behold theſe bleeding woundes, witneſſe I haue already had my puniſhment at the handes of the liuing God; Creatures may well ſpare me, <hi>at least you my friendes,</hi> allyed vnto me both in nature and country, whome the like morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity (may not I ſay the like iniquity?) makes liable vnto the ſame miſchance. Call to mind the ſaying of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour vnto the eager enemyes of the guilty Woman, <hi>He that amongst you is without ſinne, let him cast the firſt ſtone at her,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioan. 8, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Quare perſequimini me ſicut Deus, &amp; carnibus meis ſaturamini?</hi> Why do you purſue me, as if your were God,<note place="margin">Iob. 19.22</note> innocent from ſinne, pure from miſery, your ſelues? yea rather why do you purſue me as if you were more then God, eyther more wife to apprehend, or more zealous to deteſt, or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21611:24"/> more ſtronge to reuenge the greatnes of my ſinnes, that wheras He after puniſhment hath ſet me free, you to fill vp the ſuppoſed defect of his iudgment, would come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me with a new ſupply of your ſtrokes. <hi>Haue pitty, haue pitty on me, for the hand of God hath ſtroken me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe wordes would not haue moued mercileſſe harts, and ſo thoſe diſtreſſed ſoules might better (as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance they did) lift vp their eyes vnto God in holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> his complaynt:<note place="margin">Pſa. 78.27</note> 
                  <hi>Quem tu percuſsiſti perſecuti ſunt, &amp; ſuper dolorem vulnerum meorum addiderunt: ego ſum pauper &amp; dole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus tua Deus ſuſcepit me:</hi> Whom thou hadſt ſtruken they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, and added new griefe vnto my woundes: I am poore and in payne, thy ſaluation hath taken me vp. O cruelty of men! they had not pitty of me being <hi>poore,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of ayde, nor commiſeratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me bleeding <hi>in payne,</hi> not only outwardly through the woundes of body, but alſo inwardly though griefes and frights of ſoule. They bare no reſpect vnto me, as a thing particularly behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and belonging vnto thee, as one whom <hi>thy ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion tooke vp</hi> into thy handes out of thoſe ruines. If a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar or Shee-wolfe hauing a man in her pawes ſhould out of compaſſion let him free, how cruell would he be thought that ſhould ſeeke to make that man away pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vpon his eſcape? O Lord thyne anger (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſayth) is as fierce as the <hi>Shee-beare that hath loſt her whel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oſee 13.8.</note> Whence we may gather how wild and ſauage they are, that would ſtone them to death, that come bleeding from vnder the hand of thy terrible anger, <hi>Whome thou hadst ſtruken, they purſued, and added new griefe vnto my woundes.</hi> But ſhall ſuch cruelty paſſe without puniſhment? No. They ſhall receaue the greateſt puniſhment that God in his implacable anger can lay vpon men in this life, which is ſet downe in the wordes that next follow: <hi>Appone ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitatem ſuper iniquitatem eorum, &amp; non intrent in iustitiam tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: deleantur de libro viuentium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.28.29.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; cum iustis non ſcribantur.</hi> Lay vpon them iniquity vpon iniquity, and let them neuer enter into thy righteouſnes: let them be blotted out of the booke of life, and not be written amongſt the iuſt.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21611:24"/>
               <p>And this may be another reaſon of this permiſſion in regard of Puritans, to wit, for the greater obduration of the more hoat, vnmercifull and obſtinate ſort of them. For as their malice is ſuch, as they would, if they could, loade the Catholike Church with wound vpon wound, ſo God permitting miſchances to happen before the eyes of their body, that carry ſome ſhew of ſcandall, &amp; ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting from before the eyes of their ſoule the light of his grace to make due inſpection vnto them, giues them oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, wherby they <hi>heape iniquity vpon iniquity, filling their hearts,</hi> more &amp; more, <hi>with malice &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt,</hi> till being come to the meaſure of Gods appoyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>they be carried into Hell.</hi> Theſe iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God are ſo much the more terrible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they leaſt of all regard the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom they moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cern being ſo blinded &amp; deluded with the delightful imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſelfe-fancy in their interpretation of Scripture, as they neuer ſo much as apprehend the heynouſnes of their offence in conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning the perpetuall Chriſtian Tradition of the Church. I will not inſiſt vpon this poynt, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it vnto the inward ſearch of their Conſcience, deſiring them in Chriſt Ieſus, and as they tender their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, that they will call to mind how many thouſands of Heretikes haue byn in former Ages, that thought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues no leſſe ſecure of the truth then they now doe, did alledge Scriptures for their errours as faſt as they now do, and more cleere and expreſſe then they can doe any, &amp; yet now burne for euer in hell, for their contempt of the Tradition and Authority of the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons in the behalfe of them that were ſlayne, &amp; the happines of their death.</head>
               <p>TO come to the principall intendment of God, <hi>who in the midst of his iudgments, is euer mindfull of his mercyes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 33.8.</note> He permitted this miſchance for the ſame cauſe for which he permitted the misfortune of the Chriſtian army in the holy Land, whither by his ſpeciall ordinance they were
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21611:25"/> called agaynſt the Saracens.<note place="margin">Godefred. in vita Bern. l. 3. c. 4. Otto Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. in Fred. l. 1. c. 38. Baron. Tom. 12. An. 1145.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> was ſummoner of this Holy Hoſte, in which the Emperour was in perſon with other great Princes of Europe. And the Saint wro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught many miracles, as the healing of diuers that had byn borne blind and lame, to ſhew it was Gods will they ſhould goe. They went, they were diſperſed, they were killed, they dyed of Famine, very few returned backe into their countryes. A moſt ſad accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and ſo dreadfull, as it filled all Europe with lamentations and teares. Why was this done? Gods holy purpoſe heerin was, that men by that leauing their friends and country, by the pious la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the iourney,<note place="margin">Vide ep. Bern. 333.</note> by that offering their liues vnto dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for Chriſtian Religion, being cleanſed, and hauing ſatisfied for their ſinnes, might in the ſeruour of their pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance happily dy, &amp; be eternally ſaued. Some holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that liued in that Age,<note place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>annes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Abbas Caſaema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij.</note> had reuelations, wherin whileſt the whole Chriſtian world was drowned in ſorrow for the dishonour and death of their friendes, they ſaw the Angels exult in heauen, and heard them reioyce &amp; ſinge, becauſe many of their ſeates, made voyd by the fall of their fellowes, were filled agayne with the ſaued ſoules of them that dyed in that voyage. O how contrary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the iudgments of fleſh &amp; bloud are the courſes of God! who to worke the ſaluation of ſoules, little regards, yea laughes at the temporall diſgrace, ouerthrow and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a thouſand of armyes: and no wonder, ſeing in this caſe he ſpared not the bloud of his only Sonne.</p>
               <p>What can Chriſtian Piety thinke better of Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goodnes, but that he ordayned this meeting for the ſaluation and entrance into heauen of many ſoules at once, ſeing they were afore hand ſo Religiouſly prepared for death. For that day (the moſt of them) were puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Sacrament of the Church, and all of them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſanctified by the preaching of Gods holy Word, and the doctrine of Charity, <hi>which hydeth the multitude of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouerb. 10.12. 1. Pet. 4.8. Iſa. 6.3.</note> Why then may we not thinke, that as their bodyes by the weight of nature fell to the ground, ſo their ſoules with the <hi>Seraphicall winges</hi> of Charity, which the Sermon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21611:25"/> gaue them tooke their flight togeather at the ſame tyme into the boſome of God.<note place="margin">Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos oculos cordis. Eph. 1.18.</note> They that haue the eyes of their Fayth more quicke then their ſight of fleſh and bloud, will eaſily belieue there was not greater weeping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their friendes on earth for their bodyes, then was reioycing among the Angels in Heauen for their ſoules. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſaying of S. <hi>Hierome</hi> be true (and what more true being taken from the mouth of Verity it ſelfe?<note place="margin">Hier. ep. ad Heliod. Luc. 12.37. Beatiſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quos cum venerit Dominus inuenerit vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</note>) <hi>Happy the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an whom the LAST HOVRE findes imployed in the Diuine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eruice,</hi> Then were theſe men moſt happy whom the LAST HOVRE, yea moment of life, found in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>bleſt act of the Diuine ſeruice, hearing his holy Word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith great content and deuotion of ſoule.</p>
               <p>As for Proteſtants that were preſent, it is likely there were few ſuch in hart, yet it there were any, we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>pe, yea we need not doubt, of Gods mercy towardes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>hem in that moment. He endued their harts with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ght of true Fayth, with ſorrow for their ſinnes, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>uall, or at leaſt virtuall deſire of the Sacraments of the Church, and ſo they found by happy experience the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>th of that Diuine promiſe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 45. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Ezec. 18.21. 1. Pet. 3. Matth. 24.37. Hier. in qq. Hebr. Bellar. l. 4 de Chriſt. c. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>In whatſoeuer houre the ſinner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ene vnto me, I will not remember any of his ſinnes. If many that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> been incredulous in the dayes of Noe, feasting and banquetting,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> deriſion of the <hi>Deluge</hi> he threatned to come vpon them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>en they ſaw themſelues incloſed with inundations of water, cryed vnto God, and God as ſoone as they cryed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pardon, ſent vpon them the Spirit of his grace, heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> grones and ſighs of their pennance, notwithſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hydeous roaring of waues; may we not with more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ſon hope of the conuerſion of theſe that came ſponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ouſly to this Sermon? They were taken, not feaſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>d banquetting, but in an exerciſe of piety, not as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>e deriding, but as they were diligent in hearing Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>y Word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and as they were by the power therof mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ied, togeather with others, to ſorrow for their ſinnes; Could the cracke of the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber in the fall ſo drown their grones, as they paſſed not into the eare of Gods mercy? Could the duſt &amp; rubbiſh ſo hide their lifting vp of harts
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21611:26"/> and handes for pardon, as not to be perceaued by the eye of his goodnes? Can we thinke that <hi>God that loueth ſoules,</hi> brought theſe men deſirous of ſauing truth to a Sermon where the ſame was preached,<note place="margin">Sap. 11.17.</note> to dye in the very prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching therof, but that they ſhould be ſaued? He prouided them a Preacher to ſound the word of Saluation to their care; &amp; ſhall we thinke his ſpirit was wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting to print the ſame in their hart? <hi>A Sparow</hi> (though not worth a farthing) <hi>falles not to the ground without the heauenly Father;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 10.27.</note> and could men deſirous of ſauing truth for whome Chriſt dyed, fall with the ſound therof in their eare, without the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father</hi> working in their ſoules? No, no: Surely it was for their eternall happines, that he conducted them where they ſhould be ſo Religlouſly occupyed, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly diſpoſed,<note place="margin">Eue. 13.30.</note> ſo penitently affected, <hi>in that moment on which eternity dependes.</hi> Comming with <hi>the laſt,</hi> they were rewarded with <hi>the first,</hi> and they haue proued with the holy Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſal 83.11.</note> that it is <hi>a better choyce, Abiectus eſſe in domo Domini quàm habitare in tabernaculis peccatorum,</hi> To be abie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted or caſt downe to the ground in the houſe of God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liue in the Tabernacle of ſinners.</p>
               <p>Now to returne vnto the Catholikes ſlayne, ſome may obiect that they dyed ſuddainly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they did not think. I anſwere that <hi>ſuddaynes of death is a fauour</hi> in them that are prepared as theſe were. In this their death co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curred, what is good and to be wiſhed in each kind eyther of ſuddaine or expected death. The good of ſuddaynes is to be quit of the terrour of expectation of death, which <hi>many times is more terrible then death it ſelfe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> longè grauior expectata quàm il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata mors. Hier. in vita Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi.</note> They that expect death as imminent, their good is to be prepared by harty co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trition of ſinnes agaynſt it, the want wherof is the only thing feared in them that are ſuddainly taken away. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the happines of theſe men, they wanted the terrour of the expectation of death, but not the piety of prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for death, through the ſuddaines of the accident wherby they dyed, the weakenes of Nature had ſcarſe any time to feele the terrour of death: through the ſanctity of the action wherin they dyed, the power of grace had
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21611:26"/> the fitteſt commodity to make them feele contrition of their ſinnes. The expectation of death was layd before their eyes, not by the <hi>violence of ſicknes,</hi> but by <hi>the verity of Gods Word,</hi> which cauſed in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſadnes,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>according to the world, but ſadnes according to God, which</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſayth) <hi>worketh pennance with aſſured ſaluation.</hi> Hence their purpoſes to leaue ſinne were as harty as in the ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of preſent death, and their purpoſes to doe good workes as abſolute as in the prudent expectation of long life. They then reſolued to liue better then the cuſtome of other men,<note place="margin">Rapti ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ne malitia mutaret mentem. Sap. 4. 11.</note> when they thought (as they might) they ſhould liue aſwell as other men; but <hi>they were ſtraight ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away,</hi> and not put to the triall, wherein they might haue fayled aſwell as other men. In them that looke to dye, griefe for ſinne is ſtronge, but commonly ſtayned with ſome ſeruility of feare: in them that thinke to liue, though griefe for ſinne may be pure, yet commonly it is ſo weake as it doth not conquer the enſuing temptations of ſinne. The death of theſe was hidden and ſudden, hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from their eyes of fleſh, that feare might not ſtayne the purity of their pennance; ſudden, comming in the very inſtant, that tyme might not weaken the conſtancy of their purpoſes.</p>
               <p>But ſome agayne will ſay, their death was dreadfull, their bodyes bruyzed, their faces disfigured, they were not knowne of their friendes. Let S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> anſwere.<note place="margin">l. 1. de ciu. c. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Seing</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>Chriſtians belieue the death of Lazarus among doggs licking his ſores, more happy then the death of Diues in purple and fine linnen; they that lead holy liues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quid illis horrenda genera mortium obfueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. qui bene vixerunt? 1. Reg. 6. v. 24. 2. Reg. 6.6. &amp; 7.</note> 
                  <hi>what are they worſe in that they dyed terrible deaths?</hi> God will haue his children feare any the leaſt ſinne more then any the dreadfulleſt death, and therfore ſometymes he doth puniſh ſmall offences with horrible ſlaughters. The <hi>Bethſamites</hi> in the midſt <hi>of their pious ioy,</hi> for the returne of the Arke, were ſlayne by fifty thouſands, only for a curious looke: <hi>Oza</hi> that <hi>put his hand</hi> to ſaue the Arke from falling, was ſtrucken dead, becauſe he did it in leſſe reuerent manner. In the Bookes of Kings is recorded the death of an holy Prophet, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21611:27"/> vpon his working a moſt ſtrange miracle,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Reg. 13. 24. Greg. l. 3. ep. 10 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> killed by a Lion for a ſinne of meere ignorance. S. <hi>Gregory</hi> writes of many holy Monkes and Religious Officers, that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of deuotion for the greater orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the place about the tombe of S. <hi>Laurence;</hi> becauſe, though by cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and agaynſt their will they opened his Shrine and ſaw his body, fell preſently ſicke, <hi>and dyed all within ten dayes after.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae Patr. Herebert. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> libell. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In vitis Patrum</hi> we read of a godly man going <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit an Ermite his friend: As he paſſed in the ſtreete he ſaw the body of a great rich ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> famous for wickednes that had dyed a ſtill death in bed, carryed with great honour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Sepulture: When he came to the wildernes he found the Ermite that had lead an holy and auſtere life deuoured of wild beaſts. Aſtoniſhed therat with many teares, he beſought of God he might know the reaſon of this proceeding, and God thought good for our inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in like euents to reueale him the myſtery by his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. The richman amongſt many enormous crimes had done ſome ſmaller good deedes; Theſe were rewarded with peaceble death &amp; honourable exequyes, whileſt his ſoule for the other burned in fire inextinguiſhable. The E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mite with his many dayly excellent workes had min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled ſome leſſer offences, which were expiated by that horrible death, that his ſoule might goe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to enioy his Crowne.</p>
               <p>Can the world diſcerne any difference of vnhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes betwixt the death of our King <hi>Edmund</hi> the Martyr. and the death of our King <hi>Richard</hi> the Tyrant? They both were defeated in field, both killed and couered with an heape of ſlaughter, the dead bodyes of them both came into the power of their enemyes to be ſcorned. Compare the death of King <hi>Lewis</hi> the Saynt, with the death of King <hi>Antiochus</hi> the wicked, no diſſimilitude appeares in outward ſhew. Both dyed in a ſtrange country, both af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhamefull repulſe, both ſtroken with a lothſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent vlcer. And yet theſe deaths, ſuch paralells in the aye of fleſh and bloud, did differ no leſſe then Heauen &amp; Hell in the ſight of God and his Angels. <hi>Man iudgeth acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21611:27"/> to the face, God looketh into the hart:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Reg. 10. 7.</note> It is fedity of ſoule not deformity of body that makes God ſay vnto ſome, I <hi>know you not.</hi> It little importes the dead that their bodyes be knowne of their friends, who when they know them will but lay them vnder earth to be the food of wormes.<note place="margin">Matt. 25.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> That which importes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is that their ſoules be knowne of the Angels, that <hi>going out of their bodyes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; 22.</note> 
                  <hi>they may be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d by them into the boſome of Abraham, and into the euerlasting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>rnacles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet I dare ſay, their bodyes were not ſo disfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d as they may compare in deformity with the body of their crucified Lord and Sauiour,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.4.</note> of whome the Prophet ſayth, <hi>We ſaw him, and there was neyther shape nor figure in him, ſo we know him not, but made esteeme of him as of a leaper, and as of a man ſtrocken of God.</hi> It is a part of their honour they were ſo like to their Maſter, and the day shall come when <hi>the disfigured bodyes of their humility,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>shall be configured vnto the body of his clarity,</hi> then be ſo much the more beautifull, by how much now they ſeemed horrible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons for the Profit of Catholikes: and the Concluſion.</head>
               <p>TO Conclude with whome I began. You the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Children of the Church; God hath permitted this Accident to be vnto you a Warning, a Triall, an Occaſion, a Preſage: a Warning of Death, a Triall of Charity, an Occaſion of more Pennance, a Preſage of Comfort.</p>
               <p>The Deaths of theſe our Friends, are Documents how incertayne life is, and <hi>Warnings</hi> to be at all tymes, and in euery place prouided for death. God ſhewed in his Saynts what may happen vnto ſinners, he ſtroake their bodyes with ſuddayne and ſhort oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of death, to ſtrike into our ſoules longe and perpetuall meditation of death. The <hi>Chambers of impurity</hi> haue no priuiledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt death, more then the <hi>Chapells of ſanctity;</hi> nor haue
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21611:28"/> riotous feaſters in a Tauerne, a ſurer warrant of life then Religious hearers of a Sermon. Death which came vpon theſe as they were in the act of abhorring, may likewiſe ſet vpon them as they are in the act of committing ſinne. Behold here,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> as I may ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Nubes testiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a whole cloude of witneſſes,</hi> ſuddaynly diſſolued into the bloudy rayne of death, that vpon the conſenting teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of ſo many dying men, we may belieue and ſtill remember, that our life, when it is at the beſt, is but <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iacob. 4. 15. Eccl. c. 7.3</note> 
                  <hi>ad modicum parens,</hi> a ſhining cloude or vapour which in a trice, ere one can thinke is vaniſhed. The holy Ghoſt wiſheth vs to reſort often vnto the houſe of Mourning, wherein we are <hi>warned of the end of all liuing thinges.</hi> Behold here that holy Houſe of <hi>Mourning,</hi> which ringes of this Warning, with ſo ſharpe and ſhrill a ſound, as may pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate into the deafeſt hart. For the Auditors of that ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> became Preachers in their death, crying vnto all men, BE READY FOR GOD IN EVERY PLACE, AT EVERY MOMENT, <hi>who will come when men least think: This is ours, to morow will be your dying day:</hi> in this dolefull cry we muſt breath out our ſoule that the wholſome ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thereof MAY NEVER DYE IN YOVRS.</p>
               <p>This accident is a Triall, not of your Fayth (which being <hi>built on the Rocke</hi> cannot be ſhaken with the fall a roome,<note place="margin">Matt. 16.15 Matt. 5.51.</note> yea the <hi>ſame would stand, though Heauen and earth should paſſe away</hi>) but of your <hi>Charity.</hi> To loue Proteſtants that in their noble and courteous diſpoſition, pittyed the miſchance; to loue thoſe worthy Magiſtrates that being in authority did their endeauour to ſhew their humanity by their deedes. Euen as thoſe foure renowned Magiſtrats of the Citty of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſtood againſt the immanity of their brethren that would haue tyranized vpon them they had taken of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Paral. 28 v. 12. &amp; ſequent.</note> crying vnto them: <hi>Nequaquam facietis, grande enim Peccatum est. Quid vultis noua cumulare delicta?</hi> And hauing freed them out of their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, reſtored them with all kind of courteſy vnto their friends. To loue theſe I ſay, with inmoſt affections, to ſhew towardes them all kind of gratefull acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21611:28"/> as farre as you are able both by word and fact, you will be, as Duty requires, moſt foreward. You may rather feare, promptnes of Nature heerein will preuent, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne Grace, and ſo depriue you of a Reward.<note place="margin">Matt. 5.48.</note> For (as our Sauiour ſayth) <hi>If you loue them that loue you</hi> (vpon human and no higher behoofes) <hi>what reward shall you haue?</hi> But to reſpect them that inſult vpon you, to requite bitternes with loue, iniuryes with good turnes,<note place="margin">Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.10.</note> to heape <hi>the coales of charity on their heades,</hi> that caſt ſtones of cruelty at yours, <hi>This is the patience,</hi> this is the charity <hi>of Saynts,</hi> in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe whereof theſe our Saynts dyed. For the pardoning of iniuries, the rooting reuenge out of their hart was the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament &amp; laſt will they made vpon earth, in the ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that ſubiect, by a publick Notary, according to the authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Gods word. And as they haue left you the heyres of their Fayth, ſo likewiſe they haue made you the executors of their Will: neyther can you do them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny greater pleaſure, then to pray for theſe their enemyes and yours, whom for their part in that their laſt will they did aforehand eternally pardon. Excuſe this their zeale with all kind of mild interpretation within your hart; Belieue that in many it was but a paſſion in the heate of bloud, wherof perchance ſince they are abaſhed: do not forget to alleadge vnto God, our Sauiours excuſe of his crucifiers, <hi>neſciunt quid faciunt?</hi> Conſider with hope that they may happily repent: call to mynd the ſweet ſaying of S. <hi>Augustine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 1. de ciuit. c. 35.</note> ſufficient to baniſh all bitternes out of heart. <hi>In inimicis nostris latent conciues futuri, adhuc ignoti, non ſolum nobis ſed etiam ſibi:</hi> Amongſt our now enemyes ly hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thoſe that ſhallbe our fellow cittizens in Heauen, as yet vnknowne not only vnto vs, but euen to themſelues. You heard the ſeuere ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Gods iuſtice agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>That they shall neuer enter into his righteouſnes, and shallbe blotted out of the booke of life.</hi> Seeke with teares of ſorrow and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt intreaty to blot out this ſentence agaynſt them, offer vnto God your bloud (if need be) to be ſhed by their handes, for the inke wherewith to write their names a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſaued. O that there were a <hi>Moyſes</hi> now vpon
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21611:29"/> earth, ſo gracious with God, ſo charitable towardes theſe men, that he might and would effectually ſay, <hi>Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>or blot me out of the Booke of Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in your Charity towardes other, forget not the per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ection of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our owne conſcience, for which God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted this accident, to giue you an occaſion to increaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mortification &amp; pennance.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> As holy <hi>Iob</hi> vpon the new<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the dolefull death of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> children, <hi>rent in peeces his</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate <hi>in ſacke-cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n and ashes,</hi> ſo take you hold of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to caſt away from you ſuch need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe vanitye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he choyce of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art, but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of tyme hath put vpon you.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Now</hi> ſayth S. Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſment and affliction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f God,</hi> ſo that, they that are of his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Saynts muſt nyther themſelues mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tify <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd chaſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir deſires of worldly content, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> expect puniſhment &amp; reſtrain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from Gods heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nde. <hi>If we did iudge our ſelues</hi> ſayth S. Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>we shoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot be iudged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d when we are iudged we are chaſtized of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with the world we be not damned.</hi> For the heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he loueth you, ſo is he iealous of you: he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> let you liue without a Croſſe to puiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e you, that your Loue may neuer reſt vpon earth, but ſtill be flying towardes him and your true country.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ather<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prouidence he ſhewed towards his ſpeciall Saynts <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> &amp; <hi>Samuel,</hi> as Dauid ſayth, <hi>Propitius ſuit eis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vleiſcens in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> affectiones eorum,</hi> as S. Auguſtine reade, <hi>He was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ull vnto them, taking reuenge of their affections vnto life,</hi> by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>croſſe of contradictious people,</hi> who made life a torment vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem. You haue more need of admonitions in this kind now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen before, as you ſtande now in greater danger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> his life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which ſome mitigation of troubles had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de leſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bitter. The ſafe ariuall of your Hopefull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce deliuered from the daungers of ſea, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, wherein though you were in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dutifull and Diuine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpects, yet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Nature many tymes hath ſecretly a part. And if he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> your mortall fleſh ouerdeſirous of eaſe from
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21611:29"/> perſecution made you ſicke of a Pluriſy of Ioy, you ſee the carefull hand of our heauenly Surgeon comes in tyme to let you bloud.</p>
               <p>Finally God permitted this accident, to be a preſage of your approaching Comfort, &amp; of the ſpeedy ouerthrow of your hoater Aduerſaries: Their ouerthrow I meane in their errour, and hereſy, not in the life of their bodyes, which we deſire may not be ſhortned, but runne out, according to the full length of Natures race and Gods holy will. You may remember the examples of former Hereſies I brought in the ſecond Chapter, that dauncing for ioy at the miſhap of Catholikes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.7.</note> leapt themſelues out of the world. And that the ſaying of the Prophet may be true of all, <hi>Perijt memoria eorum cum ſonitu,</hi> their memory ſhall periſh with an empty ſound of exultation and ioy. Such alſo ſhalbe the Concluſion of the laſt Infidelity in the end of the world, to wit, that of Antichriſt. When the two Prophets ſhalbe ſlayne, and their bodyes ly a bloudy ſpectacle in the ſtreetes, then ſhall his followers <hi>exult and triumph. Gaudebunt ſuper illos</hi> (ſayth the Scripture) <hi>&amp; iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundabuntur, &amp; munera mittent inuicem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 11.8.</note> 
                  <hi>quia hi duo Prophetae cruciauerant eos.</hi> They ſhall make ſuch reioycing and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing, as our Aduerſaries full of the perſecuting ſpirit, now make for the bodyes of theſe two Catholike Prieſts and Preachers ſlayne in their Puritan ſtreete: ſo ſhewing the ſaying of <hi>Wiſedome</hi> to be true, <hi>ante ruina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exaltatur ſpiritus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 10.16. Dominus Ieſu inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiet ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu oris ſui. 2. Theſſ. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>8. Apoc. 11.13.</note> For this reioycing in the death of the two Prophets, is to be the laſt flaſh of Antichriſtan felicity and light, which preſently therupon <hi>by the breath our Sauiours mouth,</hi> ſhall be blowne out, and they <hi>conuerted to giue glory vnto the God of Heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as vayne and empty ioy is the Preſage of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of Hereſy, that the ſame will ſoone vaniſh out of their harts; ſo likewiſe affliction ſent on Gods ſeruants by him, is the harbinger of Comfort, that according to the prognoſtication of Saynts, the ſureſt preſage of a fayre Day is a miſty Morning, as doth ſignify the Prophet <hi>Amos.</hi> For hauing foretold a great affliction that God
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21611:30"/> would ſend vpon his people, ſtraight added theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable wordes, wherwith I will conclude this Word of Comfort. <hi>Postquam haec fecerit tibi, praeparare in occurſum Dei tui O Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos. 4.12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>quia ecce faciens nebulam matutinam:</hi> When he hath layd this affliction vpon thee, then O Iſrael, make thy ſelfe ready to go meete thy God, for behold he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes a miſt in the morning: as one ſhould ſay, when you ſee a miſt of affliction in the morning, then prepare your ſelfe for the fayre and lightſome day of comfort. We now are in the miſt of ſorrow and affliction for this miſchance, that hath caſt a miſt of new darkenes and ignorance ouer the eyes of ſome, which the light of truth ioyned with the burning flames of your charity and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and alſo with the ſhining beames of humility and mildnes, may ſoone diſſolue. And theſe Innocents that dyed in this ſo pious exerciſe of Religion, will be your Aduocats with God, your Aduocats with men; they will pleade your cauſe in Heauen, they will pleade your cauſe on earth; their bloud will in tyme mollify harts as hard as Dyamond: <hi>The voyce of their bloud hauing a better cry then that of Abell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.24</note> will penetrate into the eare of your mercifull Sauiour, into the eare of your Gratious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and obtayne more then you perchance would preſume to aske.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:21611:30"/>
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Pag.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Lin.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Errata.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Correct.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>all</cell>
                     <cell>at</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>vlt.</cell>
                     <cell>precepts</cell>
                     <cell>precept</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Conſtance</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Constantine</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>or</cell>
                     <cell>for</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>they</cell>
                     <cell>then</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>true</cell>
                     <cell>truer</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>aſtruous</cell>
                     <cell>aſtrious</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>33.</cell>
                     <cell>24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>deleatur</hi> and</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>38.</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>terrour</cell>
                     <cell>horrour</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>38.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>for that</cell>
                     <cell>that for</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>39.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>reaſon why God. &amp; <hi>deleatur</hi> why.</cell>
                     <cell>reaſon? God,</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
